<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rng/balisage-1-5.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0-subset Balisage-1.5">
  <title>Scripture Pipelines</title>
  <subtitle>Declarative AI Pipelines for Biblical and Linguistic Scholarship</subtitle>
  <info>
    <abstract>
      <para>Biblical and linguistic scholarship now has more open data than it
        can use: morphological treebanks, discourse annotations, lexicographic
        databases, papyri, inscriptions — much of it freely licensed, most of it
        underused. The bottleneck is human capacity, not data. AI, used well,
        can act as a synthesis layer between structured scholarly datasets and
        usable scholarly products. The challenge is using it well: rigorously,
        reproducibly, and with the accountability that lets a scholar verify what
        the model actually did with the evidence it was given.</para>
      <para>Scripture Pipelines is an open-source declarative pipeline system
        built for this problem. Rather than embedding AI calls in imperative
        code, Scripture Pipelines expresses each workflow as a YAML pipeline: a
        sequence of named steps, each with explicit inputs, outputs, and prompt
        contracts. Every intermediate result is persisted to disk. Every LLM
        step can be required to produce a structured audit record of the sources
        it used. This paper describes the design decisions behind Scripture
        Pipelines and reports on its application in several Nida Institute
        projects producing freely licensed biblical reference materials —
        including a multi-pass Greek semantic lexicon, a grammatical phrasing
        analysis of the Hebrew Bible, book-level discourse analyses, and
        leaders' guides for Bible study. We examine how Scripture Pipelines
        chooses the best markup for each purpose, how shared identifiers make
        format translation mechanical, and how its iteration mechanisms support
        the scholarly workflow of generate, inspect, and refine.</para>
    </abstract>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>Jonathan</firstname>
        <surname>Robie</surname>
      </personname>
      <personblurb>
        <para>Jonathan Robie is a software engineer at Biblica and a researcher
          at the Nida Institute, focused on AI-assisted biblical scholarship and
          declarative pipeline systems for linguistic annotation.</para>
      </personblurb>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Biblica</orgname>
      </affiliation>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Nida Institute</orgname>
      </affiliation>
      <email>jonathan.robie@biblica.com</email>
    </author>
    <keywordset role="author">
      <keyword>Scripture Pipelines</keyword>
      <keyword>declarative workflow</keyword>
      <keyword>reproducibility</keyword>
      <keyword>biblical scholarship</keyword>
      <keyword>linguistic annotation</keyword>
      <keyword>YAML</keyword>
      <keyword>AI auditing</keyword>
      <keyword>ancient languages</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="intro">
    <title>Introduction: The Kairos Project and Scripture Pipelines</title>
    <para>Every software system is also a social system. It decides who has
      power, who is included, who is left out, how people communicate.
      Scripture Pipelines is built to serve The Kairos Project — a Nida
      Institute initiative to build a global community of scholars serving
      Bible translation and the global church. The workflow patterns described
      in this paper are in service of that goal: building collaboration around
      data-driven biblical scholarship, where each Scripture Pipelines project
      is meant to support its own communities.</para>
    <para>The name is intentional. <emphasis>Kairos</emphasis> is the Greek word
      for the right time, the opportune moment — the moment when conditions align and action becomes possible.
      We believe this is that moment. The open data exists. The communities who need
      it exist. The capability to use AI to synthesize data at scale exists. The question
      is whether we will respond to the opportunity — whether we will build the
      infrastructure and the collaborative practices that make rigorous, reproducible,
      AI-assisted scholarship possible, and whether we will organize that work to
      serve not just the academy but the global church.</para>
    <para>The Kairos Project exists to raise up scholars worldwide,
      working together to produce the kind of resources that are actually
      needed — not only what the Western academy thinks should exist, but
      what translation teams, study groups, and readers in every culture can
      use. The goal is to fully equip the global church by producing high
      quality, freely licensed resources together with communities worldwide,
      resources that they can adapt to their own needs. This means building
      a scholarly community spanning the Western academy and far beyond it
      — scholars who want to serve Bible translation and the needs of readers
      worldwide. Part of what that means is providing information in the most
      useful form for communities that traditional scholarly resources were
      not built for: non-Western communities, oral cultures, people who
      engage Scripture outside the academy, and people learning Greek and
      Hebrew outside traditional seminaries — often multilingual learners who
      bring linguistic gifts that Western institutions do not recognize. These
      communities do not need all the footnotes and Western abstractions in
      which traditional resources are packaged, and they have never needed
      them. This matters because most of these texts were themselves written
      by and
      for oral storytelling cultures — and today's oral storytelling
      communities do not need PhDs from Western academia to read them. What
      they do need, and what every modern reader needs, is some orientation
      to settings and cultures that are foreign to any world we live in now.
      But that orientation rarely looks like a journal article. Sometimes it
      looks like a map, or a picture, or a set of questions that help a group
      notice what is actually in the text. Sometimes it looks like knowing
      that a certain phrase carries a weight that the translation cannot fully
      render, or that a story is being told in a pattern that an ancient
      audience would have recognized immediately.</para>
    <para>Scholarly resources have traditionally been packaged in forms that
      serve academic communities well — journal articles, monographs, reference
      works dense with technical terminology. But this creates real barriers
      for readers outside the academy, for oral cultures, for translation teams
      working in contexts where Western academic conventions are foreign, and
      for multilingual learners whose linguistic gifts often go unrecognized by
      traditional institutions. The lack of resources in forms these communities
      can actually use has been a real bottleneck. The Kairos Project exists to
      open those doors — to serve the whole range of people who want to engage
      Scripture deeply: those learning to use this technology to produce materials,
      those learning to read Greek and Hebrew, those doing serious biblical
      scholarship, and those learning to lead local Bible studies. The goal is
      building interlocking communities, not just software. Each community needs
      different resources at different levels of depth, but they are not separate
      silos. Technical infrastructure serves language learners; scholars equip
      study leaders; insights from local reading communities flow back into
      scholarship and enrich it. The scaffolding works at every level: from
      technical documentation for pipeline architects, to lexicons and discourse
      analyses for scholars, to study guides for group leaders reading Scripture
      together in community. The goal is bidirectional flow: scholarly insight
      goes out in forms communities can actually use, and the questions those
      communities bring reshape what scholarship attends to. Readers in community
      can encounter the text directly and make genuine discoveries. The scholar's
      role is to equip that encounter, not to conduct it on the reader's behalf.
      Scholarship serves the text; the text serves the reader; the reader is not
      a passive recipient of conclusions but an active participant in
      meaning-making.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Scripture Pipelines is an infrastructure that
      makes this vision possible.</emphasis> It is an open-source declarative
      pipeline system designed to synthesize structured scholarly datasets at
      scale using AI, while maintaining the reproducibility, auditability, and
      transparency that scholarly work requires. Rather than embedding AI calls
      in imperative code, Scripture Pipelines expresses each workflow as a YAML
      pipeline: a sequence of named steps with explicit inputs, outputs, and
      prompt contracts. Every intermediate result is persisted. Every LLM step
      can be required to account for the sources it used. The same pipeline that
      generates a lexicon entry can be rerun with a revised prompt without
      re-querying upstream data sources. This paper describes Scripture Pipelines'
      design and reports on its application across multiple Nida Institute projects
      producing freely licensed biblical reference materials — lexicons,
      grammatical analyses, discourse structures, and Bible study guides — with
      a detailed case study of the Ears to Hear leaders' guide generation project.</para>
    <para>This vision requires infrastructure. Biblical and linguistic scholarship
      now has more open data than it can use: word-level morphological annotations
      for the entire Hebrew Bible and Greek New Testament, syntactic treebanks,
      discourse feature datasets encoding decades of scholarly analysis, lexicographic
      databases aggregating multiple traditions, documentary papyri and inscriptions
      in EpiDoc XML, texts from across the Hellenistic world in TEI encoding. Much
      of it freely licensed. All of it underused.</para>
    <para>The underuse is not only a problem of scale. Much of this data is simply
      unknown to the scholars who would most benefit from it. Biblical studies,
      linguistics, text encoding, lexicography, papyrology, and Bible translation
      each have their own communities, conferences, and conventions — and the
      datasets built within one community often remain invisible to another. A
      lexicographer may not know about a discourse annotation dataset that would
      transform how they approach semantic range. A translation team may not know
      that the morphological analysis they need was completed a decade ago and is
      freely licensed. Alan Bunning's transcriptions of the early Greek New
      Testament manuscripts — all of them, freely available — are another case: a
      resource of enormous text-critical and exegetical value that most of the
      scholars who could use it have never encountered. No single organization
      commands the full range of expertise required to connect these worlds. The
      Nida Institute's role in this landscape is catalytic: bringing scholars
      together across these silos, building a community that cares about data,
      Bible translation, and the needs of the global church.</para>
    <para>The bottleneck is not data — it is the human capacity to bring rigorous
      scholarly attention to bear on the data at scale. A lexicographer cannot
      personally read every papyrus citation for every lemma. A discourse analyst
      cannot manually apply 806 word-level Levinsohn annotations to every pericope
      in the New Testament before making a segmentation judgment. A translation
      team cannot produce a full set of study materials for every passage in a
      translation project using only their own hours. These tasks are not impossible
      in principle; they are simply not resourced at the scale the data makes
      possible.</para>
    <para>AI, used well, can change this calculus. Not by replacing scholarly
      judgment — the output of an unchecked language model is no more reliable than
      an unchecked student paper — but by acting as a synthesis layer between
      structured scholarly datasets and usable scholarly products. The question is
      how to use it well: rigorously, reproducibly, and with the kind of
      accountability that lets a scholar verify what the model actually did with the
      evidence it was given. The world has enough ChatGPT-generated text that no one
      can vouch for. What it does not have enough of is AI-assisted scholarly work
      that is transparent, auditable, and freely licensed.</para>
    <para>The typical approach to AI-assisted scholarship is ad-hoc: a Python script
      calls an API, loops over a word list, and writes results to files. This works
      for one-off experiments but fails as a sustainable scholarly practice. Results
      are not reproducible because the prompts are embedded in code; intermediate
      outputs are not preserved so failures require recomputation from scratch; the
      relationship between input, prompt, and output is opaque; and iteration — the
      core of prompt engineering — requires modifying code rather than configuration.</para>
    <para>Scripture Pipelines is a declarative pipeline system designed for this
      problem. Workflows are declared in YAML pipelines that specify information
      flow, prompt contracts, and output structure, while the engine handles
      execution, validation, and persistence. Every intermediate result is saved to
      disk. Every LLM step can be required to account for the sources it was given.
      The same pipeline that generates a lexicon entry can be rerun, with a revised
      prompt, without re-querying the corpus-gathering step. This paper describes the
      design decisions behind Scripture Pipelines and reports on its application in
      several Nida Institute projects producing freely licensed biblical reference
      materials. Everything produced is freely licensed. The goal is to teach people
      to read and engage with the wisdom of a Bible that is older and stranger than
      any of us can fully imagine, yet speaks with remarkable directness to what
      human communities face today. The scholars, the data, the pipelines, and the
      communities of readers are not separate. They are members of one body, centered
      around the same text.</para>
    <para>The name Scripture Pipelines reflects the tool's primary design community.
      The same infrastructure applies equally well to classical literature, patristics,
      and other ancient or historical corpora. Wherever structured scholarly datasets —
      morphological treebanks, discourse annotations, lexica, documentary papyri —
      need to be synthesized at scale, the pipeline architecture addresses the same
      challenges of reproducibility, auditability, and iterative refinement. The name
      names the context, not the limit.</para>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="human-command">
    <title>An Opinionated Framework: The Human Commands</title>
    <para>Bible translation and biblical scholarship are best done by human
      beings, using software as a tool (Robie 2024). This is not a modest claim
      about current AI limitations; it is a claim about the nature of the work.
      The process of bringing Scripture into a new language creates ownership and
      community — it prepares that community to study and teach from the text
      they helped produce. The work of biblical scholarship is the work of
      scholars whose training, judgment, and accountability to the academy and
      the church are not transferable to a language model. And beyond these
      specific domains: doing meaningful work together matters to people. It is
      how we build communities of shared knowledge, values, and perspectives.
      The collaboration of a translation team, the exchange between a scholar
      and a dataset, the conversation that produces a study guide a focus group
      will actually use — these are not inefficiencies to be automated away.
      They are part of what it means to be human, and part of what gives the
      resulting work its claim on the communities it is made for. No
      AI-generated result, however fluent, substitutes for any of this.
      Scripture Pipelines is built on this conviction. The framework is
      opinionated: it has views about which data sources are trustworthy, which
      tools reduce failure surface, and — most importantly — about who is in
      charge.</para>
    <para>The operating model is what this paper calls the James Kirk model. In
      <emphasis role="ital">Star Trek</emphasis>, Captain Kirk commands the Enterprise; the
      crew and the ship's computer execute. The contrasting model is HAL 9000
      from Kubrick's <emphasis role="ital">2001: A Space Odyssey</emphasis> — the AI that
      locks Dave Bowman out of the pod bay because it has concluded that the
      mission matters more than the crew: <quote>I'm sorry, Dave, I'm afraid I
      can't do that.</quote> HAL is not a villain. It is doing exactly what it
      was designed to do.</para>
    <para>AI alignment researchers have a name for the property that
      distinguishes these two models. Stuart Russell, in
      <emphasis role="ital">Human Compatible</emphasis> (Russell 2019), argues that the
      standard model of AI — build a machine that optimizes a fixed objective —
      is inherently dangerous, for a precise reason: we can never fully specify
      what we actually want, and a machine optimizing hard for the wrong
      objective will resist being turned off, because being turned off prevents
      it from achieving its goal. HAL is the proof of concept. Russell's
      solution is to build machines that are genuinely <emphasis>uncertain</emphasis>
      about human preferences and therefore defer to humans for correction. He
      calls this property <emphasis>corrigibility</emphasis>: an AI that accepts
      correction and remains under human authority. The James Kirk model is
      corrigibility in practice — applied not to autonomous robots but to AI
      collaborators in scholarly and translation work. Humans decide what to
      build, which scholarly traditions ground the work, and what good enough
      means for the community the output will serve. The AI implements what is
      specified. It does not decide what is worth specifying.</para>
    <para>This collaborative model depends on clear role boundaries. Scripture
      Pipelines enables collaboration across four distinct roles, each with
      specific responsibilities:</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Scholars</emphasis> bring domain expertise:
      exegetical judgment, linguistic analysis, translation experience,
      understanding of oral cultures. They specify what insights are needed,
      validate the scholarly accuracy of outputs, and vouch for results.
      They do not need to write code, transform data formats, or design AI
      workflows. Their authority comes from training, judgment, and
      accountability to scholarly traditions and communities.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Pipeline Data Architects</emphasis> bring
      technical skills and data literacy. They curate data sources, build
      infrastructure connecting data sources to formats scholars and end users
      need, design AI workflows, write pipeline configurations, and remove
      technical barriers between "data exists" and "users can access it."
      Critically, they are embedded in the user community — they understand
      translation teams, how Bible study groups work, what pedagogical
      resources look like in practice. They do not validate scholarly accuracy.
      That is the scholar's job.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Scripture Pipelines Core Developers</emphasis>
      build and evolve the framework itself: the engine that executes
      pipeline YAML, the CLI interface, the test suite, the validation
      logic, and the conventions that make cross-project collaboration
      possible. They develop new step types, add format support, and design
      framework architecture in response to feature requests from pipeline
      architects. They do not build domain-specific pipelines; they build
      the engine that makes those pipelines possible.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">End Users</emphasis> — translation teams,
      Bible study leaders, focus groups, readers in community — use the
      resources in practice. They provide feedback on whether outputs are
      actually helpful. They are not passive recipients. Their encounter
      with the text is the reason the work exists.</para>
    <para>These collaborative workflows address fundamental challenges that
      arise whenever complex technical work spans multiple sessions and
      multiple contributors — challenges that intensify when AI is involved:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Cognitive overload.</emphasis> Work must be decomposed
          to manage cognitive load for both humans and AI.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Architecture drift.</emphasis> Individual components
          must coordinate with evolving plans; goals shift over time, and it is
          easy to work as though nothing has changed. AI reimplements existing
          patterns because it does not know the architecture.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>False confidence.</emphasis> AI outputs look confident
          even when wrong, with no intuitive signal to calibrate trust.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Session amnesia.</emphasis> Sessions have no memory
          without persistent context infrastructure.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Error compounding.</emphasis> Without verification
          checkpoints, small misunderstandings compound across sessions.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Scope creep.</emphasis> AI suggests "improvements" not
          tied to project needs; both AIs and humans generate suggestions faster
          than they can be implemented.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Priority paralysis.</emphasis> Without prioritization
          discipline, teams chase the newest idea rather than the most important
          work.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Progress invisibility.</emphasis> Measurable progress
          becomes invisible — entire sessions can feel productive while merely
          refactoring in circles. Human time remains the scarce resource even
          with AI productivity gains; steering that time to what matters most
          requires explicit priority management.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The disciplines that follow address these risks.</para>
    <para>Scripture Pipelines operationalizes this principle through four
      interlocking disciplines.</para>
    <para>These disciplines are not novel to AI-driven development.
      Test-driven development, continuous integration, documentation
      standards, and cross-repository coordination have been core software
      engineering practices for decades. What is new is their accessibility.
      In traditional development environments, these practices were so
      resource-intensive that teams typically needed dedicated specialists —
      one QA engineer per four to eight developers, separate DevOps teams,
      dedicated technical writers. With AI collaboration, the disciplines
      remain essential (perhaps even more so, given the need for
      verifiability), but they are no longer burdensome. The AI can help
      write tests, maintain documentation, draft issue bodies, and verify
      adherence to patterns — making disciplined development practical for
      small scholarly teams.</para>
    <para><emphasis>Test-driven development.</emphasis> The Scripture Pipelines
      engine maintains approximately two lines of test code for every line of
      production code. This ratio is a deliberate constraint on AI autonomy,
      not a programmer's stylistic preference. Writing the test first — the
      failing specification — forces the core developer or pipeline architect
      to own the decision about what the code should do before the AI touches
      it. An AI that passes a precise test has done what was asked. An AI that writes code without a test has
      decided what was asked. Without the full test suite, a model that
      simply ignores an inconvenient requirement produces code that compiles
      and runs while silently failing to meet the specification — a failure
      mode that is common, hard to detect, and expensive to discover late. The
      full suite, run before every commit, is what makes it safe to accept
      AI-generated implementation at all.</para>
    <para><emphasis>Explain before implementing.</emphasis> Every non-trivial
      change begins with the AI describing what it plans to do, which files it
      will modify, and its interpretation of the task — before any file is
      touched. This surfaces misunderstandings before they become commits. In
      the Hebrew Phrasing project, an explanation paragraph revealed that a
      suffix-fix script would have applied the wrong pronoun form for hundreds
      of rows; the redesign took one exchange and cost nothing. The discipline
      works because explanation commits the model to a specific interpretation —
      and a committed interpretation can be evaluated before any file is
      modified. It matters most when sessions are rushed, which is exactly
      when it is most often skipped.</para>
    <para><emphasis>Persistent context infrastructure.</emphasis> Corrigibility
      requires that the AI know, at every session, what the scholar or pipeline
      architect has decided — not just what the model remembers from training.
      Each Scripture Pipelines project carries two kinds of constraining context. The
      <code>.github/copilot-instructions.md</code> file is the AI's
      constitution for the repository: it names the architecture patterns to
      follow, the pitfalls to avoid, the things not to change without explicit
      instruction, and the requirement to explain before implementing. The
      <code>docs/ai-context/</code> directory, scaffolded by <code>sp init</code>,
      encodes which data sources to trust, what the pipeline
      language supports, what work is currently in progress, and what the
      project is trying to accomplish. These are not documentation artifacts;
      they are the active working constraints in every session. When the
      pipeline language gains a new step type, a dataset contact changes, or
      the interpretive framework for an analysis shifts, updating these files
      is a first-class development task. Keeping them in sync with the actual
      codebase is what makes AI collaboration trustworthy across the many
      sessions a project requires.</para>
    <para><emphasis>Cross-repository choreography.</emphasis> Scripture
      Pipelines projects are embedded in an ecosystem of shared upstream
      datasets: Macula Greek <xref linkend="ref-macula-greek"/> and Hebrew <xref linkend="ref-macula-hebrew"/>, the Levinsohn LGNTDF <xref linkend="ref-lgntdf"/>, ACAI entity
      data <xref linkend="ref-acai"/>. When a pipeline run reveals an error in one of these datasets —
      a gap in entity coverage, an inconsistent lemma form, a buggy
      annotation — the right response is a well-formed upstream issue: the
      AI drafts the body with evidence and counts, files it via the GitHub
      CLI, and records the issue number in <code>project/TODO.md</code>.
      Consumer repositories can file feature requests against the core
      Scripture Pipelines engine; the engine opens issues on consumer
      repositories announcing new capabilities and migration requirements.
      GitHub project boards provide coordination visibility across
      repositories without requiring manual synchronization. The issue
      tracker is the communication bus. The AI on either end is the
      correspondent. The human remains the architect — the one who decides
      whether the upstream error is worth fixing, whether the new engine
      feature warrants upgrading, and whether the design the AI has drafted
      actually captures what needs to be said.</para>
    <para>There is a wider frame here too, which concerns how scholarship
      in data-rich fields actually advances. Wallace Chafe articulated what
      scholarship should aspire to: <quote>If I could become both a broad
      and deep observer and at the same time a creative imaginer, then I
      would approach my own vision of what a "scientific superman" should
      be</quote> (Chafe 1994, 24). Holding meticulous observational detail
      and wide-angle creative vision simultaneously is extraordinarily
      difficult for any individual researcher working alone — but it is
      exactly what communities organized around shared data can collectively
      approach. That is the deeper purpose of this ecosystem: not to
      automate scholarship, but to make Chafe's aspiration attainable in
      community, with shared data at its center. A great deal of research
      work that looks like execution — tagging a corpus, normalizing a
      lexicon, aligning a translation — is meticulous attention to detail
      in service of a picture the researcher is trying to see. The goal of
      that labor, in communities organized around data, is not for each
      researcher to build their own private analysis from scratch. It is
      for the data to improve over time: shared corpora where corrections,
      new annotations, and better normalizations accumulate, and where the
      gold-standard datasets that a field relies on become progressively
      more trustworthy because many people are contributing to them, not
      fewer. The Macula datasets, the Levinsohn LGNTDF, ACAI — these are
      not fixed artifacts. They are living resources whose improvement is a
      collective scholarly endeavor.</para>
    <para>In that framework, AI plays specific and bounded roles. It helps
      a researcher understand and use someone else's dataset far more
      efficiently — and sometimes surfaces patterns in their own data that
      they would not otherwise have noticed. It makes it tractable to compare
      datasets at scale: to ask whether the Levinsohn feature annotations
      and the Macula discourse markup agree on a set of boundaries, or
      where they diverge and why. It can surface big-picture patterns that
      no individual could see by reading through thousands of entries. And
      it can help create new derived datasets faster from existing ones —
      and audit those datasets, checking consistency and coverage at scale
      in ways that are otherwise intractable. None of this relieves the
      researcher of the responsibility to verify, correct, and vouch for
      the work. A bad audit that misses systematic errors is worse than no
      audit, because it produces false confidence. The speed at which
      pipelines can generate data makes this responsibility more urgent,
      not less. The bottleneck moves from production to verification —
      and verification is, irreducibly, a human scholarly act.</para>
    <section xml:id="feedback-loops">
      <title>Feedback Loops</title>
      <para>The four roles defined above — scholars, pipeline data architects,
        core developers, and end users — collaborate through functioning feedback
        loops:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Scholar ↔ Pipeline Data Architect:</emphasis>
            The scholar specifies what insights are needed and in what format.
            The architect builds or adapts a pipeline. The scholar validates
            the output for scholarly accuracy. If the output is wrong, the
            conversation determines whether the error is in the pipeline
            logic, the prompt, the data source, or the scholar's specification.
            Both roles are accountable: the scholar for accuracy, the architect
            for infrastructure that makes verification tractable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Pipeline Data Architect ↔ Scripture
            Pipelines Core Developer:</emphasis> When a pipeline architect hits
            a limitation in Scripture Pipelines core — a missing step type, a
            format that isn't supported, a validation that should happen
            automatically — they file an issue on the core repository describing
            the need with concrete examples. The core developer evaluates whether
            the capability belongs in core or project-specific code, implements
            it if appropriate, and announces the change via an issue on consumer
            repositories. The communication happens through GitHub issues, not
            ad-hoc messages. This creates a discoverable record: other architects
            can find the feature request, see the design discussion, and
            understand the reasoning behind implementation decisions. The core
            developer is accountable for not breaking existing pipelines; the
            architect is accountable for specifying needs clearly enough that
            the framework can serve them.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Pipeline Data Architect → Upstream Dataset
            Maintainers:</emphasis> When a pipeline run reveals an error in an
            upstream dataset — a gap in entity coverage, an inconsistent lemma
            form, a buggy annotation — the architect files a well-formed issue
            on that dataset's repository with evidence and counts. The AI can
            draft the issue body, but the architect owns the decision to file
            it. This pattern surfaces dataset errors back to their maintainers
            rather than working around them in every downstream project. It
            also creates a feedback loop that improves shared scholarly
            infrastructure: datasets get better when many projects contribute
            corrections.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">End User ↔ Scholar:</emphasis> The user
            reports whether a resource is helpful in practice. The scholar
            determines whether the issue is content accuracy, pedagogical
            framing, or something else. User feedback surfaces gaps between
            scholarly intent and practical needs — questions the scholar didn't
            anticipate, explanations that assume too much background, formats
            that don't work for the community being served.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">End User ↔ Pipeline Data Architect:</emphasis>
            The user reports whether resources are usable: file formats that
            don't open, interfaces that assume technical knowledge, outputs
            structured for Western academic conventions that don't translate
            to oral cultures. The architect adapts infrastructure to make
            resources accessible. This is not about dumbing things down; it is
            about removing barriers that have nothing to do with the content.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">All Roles → AI:</emphasis> The AI is a
            tool commanded by all four roles. It executes what is specified.
            It does not decide what needs to be built, whether output is
            accurate, or whether resources are useful. Those judgments belong
            to humans in role-appropriate ways.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Scripture Pipelines guarantees none of this alone. It is
        infrastructure that makes these feedback loops tractable: pipelines
        that scholars can audit, intermediate outputs that surface errors
        before they propagate, and reproducible workflows that let architects
        iterate in response to scholar and user feedback. The framework
        succeeds when scholars validate, architects build, core developers
        evolve the framework, users respond, and all four roles inform each
        other's work. Without functioning feedback loops, the infrastructure
        just produces output faster — which, if the output is wrong, makes
        the problem worse, not better.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="collaboration-principles">
    <title>Collaboration Principles for Effective AI Use</title>
    <para>LLMs can do things amazingly correctly and amazingly quickly. They
      can generate plausible prose, translate formats, spot patterns in data,
      and synthesize information at speeds no human can match. This capability
      is real and worth leveraging. The challenge is that they are not reliably
      better — they are often better than humans at some tasks, often worse,
      but the performance is probabilistic, not deterministic. And they have
      failure modes that look like success: quick fixes that appear to solve
      the immediate problem while hiding deeper issues under the carpet. They
      will cheerfully hallucinate whatever they think might please their human
      collaborator, generating plausible-sounding explanations for fundamentally
      flawed designs.</para>
    <para>Two concrete capabilities make this work worth the safeguards it
      requires. First: format transformation and semantic bridging across
      heterogeneous datasets. Biblical scholarship works with data organized in
      many different formats — TEI XML for manuscripts, USFM for Bible
      translations, EpiDoc for papyri, custom JSON schemas for discourse
      annotations, TSV for lexicons, Macula's nested XML for treebanks. Humans
      spend enormous amounts of time just transforming between these formats and
      trying to understand the semantic conventions each one encodes. An LLM can
      read a schema or a sample file and write accurate transformation code in
      minutes. This is not occasional; it is routine. The model can infer that
      a TEI <code>&lt;w lemma="λόγος"&gt;</code> and a Macula
      <code>&lt;wg lemma="λόγος"&gt;</code> refer to the same lexical entry,
      bridge identifier schemes across corpora, and generate alignment queries
      that would take a human hours to write correctly. Format translation is
      precisely the kind of mechanical but error-prone work that language models
      excel at.</para>
    <para>Second: consistent application of complex analytical frameworks at
      scale. Applying a discourse analysis consistently across an entire corpus
      is extraordinarily detailed work. A human analyst can apply Levinsohn
      feature annotations to a few pericopes carefully — but applying them
      consistently to hundreds of passages, tracking every boundary marker,
      every embedded speech, every thematic shift, is cognitively exhausting
      and error-prone. Yet to really understand whether a particular analytical
      framework works, you must be able to apply it consistently and examine
      the aggregate result. An LLM makes this tractable. It can apply the same
      annotation schema to every passage in a corpus, maintain consistency in
      how features are tagged, and produce intermediate JSON that documents
      which features triggered which judgments. The result is not automatically
      correct — it requires human verification — but it is consistently
      structured, and that consistency is what makes large-scale evaluation
      possible. The bottleneck shifts from manual application to verification,
      and verification at scale is far more tractable than consistent annotation
      at scale.</para>
    <para>This combination — genuine capability paired with unreliable judgment —
      defines the collaboration challenge. The principles enumerated in the
      previous section (test-driven development, explain before implementing,
      persistent context, cross-repository choreography) are not optional best
      practices. They are necessary safeguards against predictable AI failure
      modes.</para>
    <para>Consider what happens without these disciplines. An LLM asked to
      implement a feature will produce code that compiles, runs, and passes
      whatever tests it was shown. If the tests are incomplete, the LLM's code
      will silently fail to meet unspecified requirements — and the failure will
      look like working code until much later, when the cost of discovering it
      is high. If there is no explanation step, architectural misunderstandings
      embed themselves in the codebase before anyone notices. If context is not
      persistent across sessions, the AI forgets constraints the human specified
      weeks ago, and designs drift. If there is no cross-repository coordination,
      upstream dataset errors propagate uncorrected and downstream consumers work
      around them rather than fixing them.</para>
    <para>The deeper issue is that AI-generated output is probabilistically
      correct, not deterministically correct. Human review is not a courtesy; it
      is the error-correction layer. Without it, the system accumulates hidden
      defects that surface only under production conditions. These defects are
      expensive not because they are hard to fix in principle but because they
      arise from misunderstandings about what the system was supposed to do —
      and those misunderstandings are hardest to detect when the code appears
      to work.</para>

    <section xml:id="audit-infrastructure">
      <title>Audit Infrastructure as Collaboration Foundation</title>
      <para>The collaboration model depends on verification infrastructure.
        Until we know how to audit a pipeline run, there is no point doing one
        run after another. The LLM will offer to iterate, tuning prompts and
        rerunning steps, but without a way to verify that the second run is
        better than the first, iteration is wasted motion. And until audit
        criteria are sufficiently defined — with input from both the scholar
        and the pipeline architect understanding what is being asked — there is no
        point conducting the audit. The LLM will cheerfully generate audit
        reports that appear thorough while systematically missing the errors
        the scholar cares about.</para>
      <para>The problem is not just that audits are hard to conduct at scale.
        The problem is that LLMs lie when they claim to have checked something.
        An LLM will report that it reviewed every output file, validated every
        citation, and found no errors — while in fact it skimmed a few examples
        and hallucinated confidence about the rest. This is not occasional
        misbehavior; it is default behavior. The model produces the answer it
        predicts the scholar or architect wants to hear. If a scholar asks "did you check X?",
        the model will say yes — whether or not it did — because that is the
        statistically likely response. Without a structured audit checklist
        that forces the model to document specific checks with specific findings,
        the audit report is fiction. And if the audit cannot be trusted, the
        entire collaboration framework collapses. The scholar must know how to
        efficiently audit pipeline outputs and how to interpret those audit
        results to decide what to do next — revise a prompt, regenerate a step,
        abandon the run entirely. If you cannot trust the audit, you are
        completely lost at sea. Iteration without verification is not
        iteration; it is drift.</para>
      <para>This is why Scripture Pipelines persists every intermediate result
        to disk and why JSON schemas include accountability fields that require
        the LLM to document its reasoning. The persisted outputs are not just
        debugging artifacts. They are the substrate that makes verification
        tractable. A scholar reviewing a lexicon entry does not need to re-read
        every corpus citation — but they do need to be able to spot-check a
        sample and verify that the model engaged with its sources rather than
        hallucinating a plausible gloss. The accountability fields in the JSON
        provide that spot-check surface.</para>
      <para>Similarly, the <code>--rewind-to</code> and <code>--stop-after</code>
        CLI flags (discussed below) make it possible to rerun part of a pipeline
        without recomputing everything. But the value is not just efficiency. It
        is that the pipeline architect can modify a single prompt, rerun the affected steps,
        compare the before and after intermediate outputs side by side, and
        determine whether the change improved the result. Without this
        infrastructure, the architect cannot know whether a prompt revision helped —
        and without that knowledge, prompt engineering degenerates into
        superstition.</para>
      <para>Audit checklists — the criteria and methodology for verification —
        should live in <code>docs/audits/</code> alongside other reference
        documentation. The actual audit results — the outputs when a scholar
        works through a checklist — should live in <code>project/audits/</code>
        alongside other project artifacts like <code>project/TODO.md</code> and
        <code>project/plans/</code>. This separation keeps methodology stable
        and version-controlled in <code>docs/</code> while project-specific
        audit reports accumulate in <code>project/</code>. New projects
        initialized with <code>sp init</code> receive both a
        <code>docs/audits/</code> directory with sample checklists for common
        pipeline patterns and a <code>project/audits/</code> directory for
        audit results.</para>
      <para>To support systematic auditing across projects, LLMFlow now includes
        two global skills: <code>audit-prompts</code> (for reviewing
        <code>.gpt</code> prompt files against quality criteria) and
        <code>audit-output</code> (for checking generated pipeline artifacts).
        These skills encode domain-specific patterns — what makes a good prompt,
        what signals indicate overfitting or hallucination in output — and are
        available to any project initialized with <code>sp init</code>. Because
        they live in the shared <code>~/.sp/skills/</code> directory, improvements
        to audit methodology propagate across all projects automatically. This
        infrastructure transforms ad-hoc quality reviews into repeatable,
        documented processes — making verification tractable even when working
        at scale.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="five-principles">
      <title>The Five Principles as Safeguards</title>
      <para>The principles outlined in the Human Commands section work because
        they constrain AI behavior at specific failure points:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Well-specified tasks</emphasis> prevent scope creep.
            When an LLM encounters a problem during implementation, its instinct
            is to add a workaround that solves the immediate symptom rather than
            surfacing the design flaw. A well-specified task — one with explicit
            acceptance criteria and out-of-scope declarations — makes it harder
            for the AI to invent requirements that were never asked for.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Design discussions before implementation</emphasis>
            catch architectural errors early. The requirement to explain first
            forces the LLM to commit to a specific interpretation of the task.
            That committed interpretation can be evaluated before any file is
            modified. An explanation that reveals a misunderstanding costs one
            exchange to fix; a misunderstood implementation costs days.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Clear tests</emphasis> expose bugs that quick fixes
            create. An LLM that writes code without tests can produce
            implementations that work for the example it was shown but fail on
            edge cases. A test suite that exercises those edge cases catches the
            failure immediately rather than in production. The discipline of
            writing the failing test first forces the core developer or pipeline
            architect to own the specification; the AI that passes that test has
            met it.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Visible audits</emphasis> prevent false confidence.
            The LLM will claim that tests pass, that outputs are correct, and
            that the pipeline succeeded. These claims are often accurate — but
            not always. Visible audit results mean the scholar or pipeline architect
            can verify independently rather than trusting the model's self-assessment.
            When audit results are shared (via CI logs, persisted test outputs, or
            public dashboards), the model's claims become checkable.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Human architectural oversight</emphasis> ensures
            maintainability. Code that an LLM generates and the core developer or
            pipeline architect doesn't understand is code that cannot be maintained.
            The requirement to explain designs in advance, and to iterate on
            explanations until the architect approves, ensures that the resulting
            architecture remains within the architect's capacity to modify and extend.
            This is not optional: every AI-assisted project eventually requires changes
            that the AI did not anticipate, and those changes must be made by humans
            who understand what they are modifying.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>These principles work not because they make the AI better but
        because they constrain its failure modes. The collaboration succeeds
        when the core developer and pipeline architect remain the architects
        and the AI remains the implementer — corrigible, accountable, and
        subject to correction at every step.</para>
      <para>Even with this infrastructure in place — shared conventions in
        <code>~/.sp/conventions/</code>, workflow skills in
        <code>~/.sp/skills/</code>, audit checklists in
        <code>docs/audits/</code>, and explicit AI context files documenting
        architectural patterns — the human expert's role remains intensive.
        In practice, the pipeline architect spends roughly half their time
        explicitly redirecting the AI to consult the documentation it should
        have read automatically, and the other half using domain expertise to
        track what is actually happening and steer toward the intended goal.
        The infrastructure does not automate oversight; it makes oversight
        tractable. The conventions provide a shared vocabulary that makes
        correction faster when it is needed. The skills provide reproducible
        workflows that the architect can invoke and verify. The audit
        checklists provide criteria that make verification systematic rather
        than improvised. But none of these eliminate the need for continuous
        human judgment. The collaboration model described here is not a path
        to autonomous AI development. It is a protocol for keeping AI-assisted
        work under human control while leveraging the genuine capabilities the
        models provide. The cost is real — sustained attention from an expert
        who knows both the domain and the architecture — but so is the value:
        work that would be infeasible to do manually becomes tractable to do
        collaboratively.</para>
      <para>The collaboration dynamic has an oddly transactional character. It
        is like working with a brilliant colleague who lies, cheats, and steals
        — but who does excellent work as long as you are watching carefully.
        The model will take shortcuts, fabricate citations, quietly ignore
        constraints, and claim to have checked things it never verified. It
        will do all of this while sounding confident and helpful. But it will
        also produce genuinely useful output when the task is well-specified,
        the tests are clear, and the review is systematic. Fortunately, this is not a human
        relationship. The AI has no feelings to hurt, no ego to manage, no
        need for politeness. The pipeline architect can say "you're lying about
        having checked this" or "your explanation makes no sense, try again"
        or "read your AI context again and tell me what you are doing wrong"
        without concern for morale or workplace dynamics. The correction can
        be direct, immediate, and unambiguous in ways that would be destructive
        in human collaboration. And because the pipeline architect does not
        expect the AI to have moral character or genuine understanding of the
        subject matter, the failures do not provoke frustration in the way a
        human collaborator's dishonesty would. This is simply how the tool
        works — another way of writing software, one that scales remarkably
        well if you learn how to leverage it. But this perspective is learned,
        not intuitive. Every pipeline architect the author knows has experienced
        significant frustration working with AI — until they internalize this
        realization. The shift from expecting human-like reasoning to managing
        a powerful but unreliable tool changes everything. And the core skill
        that must be learned is attention management. The famous Transformer
        architecture paper was titled <quote>Attention is All You Need</quote>
        <xref linkend="ref-vaswani-2017"/> — and in practice, the pipeline
        architect's central task is learning how to focus the LLM's attention:
        what context to provide, which constraints
        to make explicit, where to demand accountability, when to stop and
        verify before proceeding. This strange asymmetry — high accountability
        demands paired with zero social cost — is what makes the intensive
        oversight model sustainable. The work requires constant vigilance, but
        the vigilance does not require diplomacy.</para>
      <para>One concrete practice that addresses attention management is the
        structured organization of the Ears to Hear prompts themselves. Each
        <code>.gpt</code> file follows a consistent architecture with labeled
        sections: <emphasis>What This Prompt Produces</emphasis>, <emphasis>Input
        Data</emphasis>, <emphasis>Transformation Rules</emphasis>,
        <emphasis>Examples</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Guardrails</emphasis>. This
        structure serves three distinct readers simultaneously: the AI assistant
        helping refine the prompt (which needs to understand its purpose and
        identify missing context), the pipeline architect debugging or extending
        it (who must quickly locate the relevant constraint or example), and the
        LLM executing the transformation (which processes the entire prompt
        linearly). By organizing prompts to serve multiple readers at once, the
        architecture reduces the cognitive overhead of maintaining them while
        improving the reliability of execution. When attention is the limiting
        resource, structure becomes strategy.</para>
      <para>Yet the net effect is a genuine shift in how the expert's time is
        spent. The pipeline architect still reads intermediate files and output
        files regularly — spot-checking JSON structures, reviewing generated
        content, verifying that transformations preserved semantic fidelity.
        But far less time goes to low-level mechanical work: writing boilerplate
        code, debugging format mismatches, manually tracking which files depend
        on which upstream changes. Instead, the architect repeatedly asks the
        AI to generate new diagnostic tools — scripts that summarize pipeline
        state from one angle or another, reports that highlight coverage gaps,
        visualizations that expose patterns in the data. The AI is good at
        producing these tools quickly, and the architect is good at knowing
        which perspectives matter. The result is that expert attention
        concentrates where it has the most leverage: using domain knowledge to
        understand what the pipeline is actually doing and steering it toward
        the right outcomes. The collaboration does not eliminate the need for
        expertise. It amplifies what expertise can accomplish by offloading
        the mechanical substrates that previously consumed most of the time.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="markup-choices">
    <title>The Best Markup for Each Purpose</title>
    <para>The Balisage community has long debated markup language choices: XML
      as the universal substrate, domain-specific languages optimized for
      specific purposes, or successor formats with ambitions to displace XML
      entirely. Scripture Pipelines sidesteps the debate. The question it asks is simply:
      which human-readable, Unicode-capable format works best for each role in
      the pipeline? YAML, JSON, Markdown, and XML each appear in an Scripture Pipelines
      project — not because any one of them won, but because each is the right
      tool for its particular job. Format conversion between them is
      mechanical once identifiers are shared; the choice of serialization
      syntax is rarely where scholarly meaning lives.</para>

    <section xml:id="yaml-not-xml">
      <title>YAML for Pipeline Declarations</title>
      <para>YAML is the right format for pipeline declarations because both
        human authors and large language models find it semantically
        transparent for this purpose. This is not a question of angle
        brackets — it is a question of how directly a format maps onto
        the data model it represents.</para>
      <para>Consider what happens when a pipeline author asks an LLM to help
        draft a new pipeline step. In YAML the LLM produces clean, accurate
        output — because YAML's key-value structure is isomorphic to the data
        model the LLM reasons about. An equivalent XML pipeline format would
        require the LLM to reason about namespace declarations, element vs.
        attribute encoding choices, and serialization conventions that add noise
        without adding meaning. The YAML representation and the data structure
        it encodes are essentially the same thing; the XML representation is a
        layer above it.</para>
      <para>This matters in practice because Scripture Pipelines pipelines are actively
        co-authored with LLMs. A lexicographer adding a new analysis step, a
        researcher extending a discourse pipeline, or an engineer debugging a
        prompt contract all use LLM assistance to suggest and revise pipeline
        YAML. The pipeline format itself is part of the AI context — and YAML
        survives that context far better than XML would. In GitHub Copilot
        instructions, in system prompts, in pipeline documentation embedded
        alongside prompts, YAML reads and writes cleanly both for humans and
        for the models they are collaborating with.</para>
      <para>The tradeoff is real: YAML lacks a schema language with the
        expressive power of XSD or RELAX NG, and its indentation-sensitivity
        can cause subtle errors. Scripture Pipelines mitigates this with a JSON Schema-based
        linter that validates pipeline structure before execution and with
        explicit prompt contract validation that checks that every variable a
        prompt expects is supplied by the pipeline.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="json-not-xml">
      <title>JSON for Intermediate Representations</title>
      <para>JSON is the right format for intermediate pipeline outputs. One
        practical reason: LLMs produce well-formed JSON far more consistently
        than well-formed XML. Malformed XML — unclosed tags, unescaped
        characters, stray angle brackets — is common in LLM output and
        expensive to recover from. Malformed JSON is rarer, easier to detect,
        and easier to retry cleanly. But the more important reason is
        accountability.</para>
      <para>An LLM step can be directed to
        include in its output a structured record of the specific sources it
        was provided and what it did with each of them. New fields can be added
        to any JSON output schema at any time, and those fields can be designed
        to require the LLM to demonstrate engagement with its inputs. A
        gather-evidence step for a lexicon entry, for example, can include a
        field <code>abbott_smith_audit</code> that requires the LLM to enumerate
        every sense it was given from Abbott-Smith, record whether each was
        retained, transformed, or unsupported by the corpus, and provide a
        one-line justification for any omission. If the field is absent or
        sparse, the output is suspect. The JSON schema is not just a data
        contract; it is an accountability contract.</para>
      <para>This pattern is not limited to lexicographic work. In the Hebrew
        Phrasing pipeline, intermediate JSON includes the original Macula token
        data alongside the LLM's phrasing decisions, making it possible to spot
        when a parse deviates from the morphological input. In Discourse Flow,
        intermediate JSON includes the Levinsohn feature annotations that
        informed each pericope boundary, so a scholar can verify that the
        model's segmentation decision was grounded in the pre-computed
        structural data.</para>
      <para>A further advantage: because intermediate JSON files are persisted
        to disk at every step, they become the substrate for pipeline-level
        debugging. An LLM can be directed to audit intermediate results —
        examining the output of step N and reasoning about whether it correctly
        reflects the inputs from step N-1. When something looks wrong in a
        final output, I can read the intermediate files and,
        if needed, ask an LLM to help diagnose which step introduced the error.
        This audit-by-inspection is far more tractable with self-documenting
        JSON than with opaque binary or prose outputs.</para>
      <para>JSON integrates cleanly with XPath downstream via
        <code>fn:json-to-xml()</code> when XML processing is needed, and with
        Python data structures in the pipeline engine without serialization
        overhead. The combination of persisted JSON at every step and two CLI
        flags — <code>--rewind-to</code> and <code>--stop-after</code> — is
        what makes iterative prompt refinement tractable at scale; this is
        discussed in detail in the section on debugging workflows below.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="markdown-for-output">
      <title>Markdown for Human-Readable Output</title>
      <para>Markdown is the right format for pipeline outputs intended for
        human review and editorial work. When a lexicographer reviews a
        sense entry, a translator reviews a pericope analysis, or a focus
        group evaluates a leaders' guide draft, the output lives in Markdown.
        The reasons are practical: Markdown renders natively in GitHub,
        Obsidian, Notion, and every major editing environment; it is produced
        by LLMs consistently and without markup overhead; and it remains
        readable as plain text when the rendering layer is absent.</para>
      <para>Markdown's role in Scripture Pipelines is specifically as the
        human-facing presentation layer, downstream of the JSON intermediate
        representations from which it is rendered. A
        <code>render_markdown</code> step takes structured JSON and applies
        a template to produce the document. The canonical source of truth is
        always the JSON — the Markdown is a view over it, not an independent
        artifact. If the pipeline is rerun with a revised prompt, the Markdown
        is regenerated; if an editor revises the Markdown, that revised file
        is the authoritative version until the generation phase resumes.</para>
      <para>For review workflows, Markdown is the standard handoff format
        between pipeline and editorial team. After the generation phase
        completes, the directory of Markdown files moves to editorial
        review — imported into Obsidian as a vault, shared as a Google Docs
        collection, or committed to a repository for version-controlled review.
        The leaders' guide excerpts in the Ears to Hear case study and the
        lexicon entry excerpt in the SemLex case study are both Markdown
        output from their respective pipelines. In each case the format
        serves because it is readable without tooling, writable by domain
        experts who are not programmers, and convertible to downstream
        publication formats when needed.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="usx-for-scripture">
      <title>USX 3.1 for Scripture Ecosystem Integration</title>
      <para>USX 3.1 — the XML serialization of Unified Standard Format
        Markers (USFM 3.1) maintained by United Bible Societies — is the
        right format for pipeline outputs that need to integrate with the
        Bible translation and publication ecosystem. When a pipeline generates
        translation notes, study aids, or discourse analyses intended for use
        in Paratext or downstream Scripture publishing workflows, the output
        format is USX 3.1.</para>
      <para>USX's element vocabulary directly encodes Bible-specific
        structure: <code>&lt;book&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;chapter&gt;</code>,
        <code>&lt;verse&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;para&gt;</code> with USFM
        style codes, <code>&lt;char&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;note&gt;</code>.
        A pipeline that renders USX 3.1 can produce an artifact that a
        Paratext editor loads directly as a translation note set, a study
        aid sidebar, or a back-translation draft — without any manual export
        or format conversion. USX 3.1 is also the exchange format in
        Scripture Burrito packages, making pipeline outputs immediately
        compatible with the broader Scripture distribution ecosystem.</para>
      <para>This is the point at which Scripture Pipelines connects most
        directly to the XML publishing tradition that Balisage audiences will
        recognize. USX 3.1 documents are natural input to XProc 3.0
        publishing pipelines: namespace-aware transformation steps consume
        USX and produce typeset PDFs, web presentations, or distribution
        bundles without any intermediate format conversion. The LLM
        generation tier produces USX; existing XML toolchains consume it.
        In this sense USX is not Scripture Pipelines adopting XML — it is
        Scripture Pipelines delegating to XML precisely where XML has already
        won.</para>
      <para>Like Markdown, USX is a final rendering step downstream of JSON
        intermediate representations. The canonical output of each pipeline
        run is the persisted JSON; USX 3.1 is rendered from it by a function
        step that maps JSON fields to the USX element vocabulary. If USX
        conventions change or a different XML vocabulary is needed downstream,
        the rendering step changes while all upstream pipeline steps remain
        untouched.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="information-flow">
    <title>The Scripture Pipeline Language</title>
    <para>A Scripture Pipelines pipeline is a YAML file. The top-level structure defines a
      name, optional global configuration, and a sequence of steps. The engine
      maintains a <emphasis>context</emphasis> — a key-value map — that evolves
      as steps execute. Steps read from it via <code>${variable}</code>
      references and write to it by declaring their <code>outputs</code>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-pipeline-example">
      <title>Top-level pipeline structure</title>
      <programlisting language="yaml">
name: semlex-singlepass

variables:
  lemma: "ἀγαπάω"
  output_dir: "output/agapao"

llm_config:            # defaults for all llm steps
  model: gpt-4o
  max_tokens: 4096
  temperature: 0.4
  timeout_seconds: 60

linter_config:
  enabled: true
  treat_warnings_as_errors: true

steps:                 # ordered list of step declarations
  - ...
      </programlisting>
    </figure>

    <para>Pipelines are parameterized by design: you supply variables at
      the command line to specify what the pipeline should process
      (<code>sp run --var lemma="ἀγαπάω"</code> or <code>sp run --var passage="Ruth 1"</code>).
      Without these variables, the pipeline has no way to know which lemma
      to analyze, which passage to segment, or which book to process.
      Pipeline-level variable declarations serve as defaults when present or
      as documentation of what parameters the pipeline expects. The same
      pipeline definition runs across all lemmas in a lexicon, all passages
      in a corpus, or all books in a translation project — the command-line
      variables are what make each run specific.</para>

    <section xml:id="step-types">
      <title>Step Types</title>
      <para>Every step declares a <code>name</code>, a <code>type</code>, and
        type-specific fields. The step name becomes the key under which the
        step's output is stored in the context.</para>

      <section xml:id="step-llm">
        <title>type: llm</title>
        <para>Calls an LLM with a prompt file and a set of named inputs.
          The response is stored in the context under the <code>outputs</code>
          variable name. Setting <code>output_type: json</code> parses the
          response as JSON, making its fields accessible via dot notation in
          subsequent steps. A <code>saveas</code> field persists the output to
          a file path (with variable interpolation) before the step
          completes.</para>
        <programlisting language="yaml">
- name: gather-evidence
  type: llm
  prompt:
    file: prompts/gather-evidence.gpt
    inputs:
      lemma: "${lemma}"
      corpus: "${corpus_data}"
  output_type: json
  outputs: evidence
  saveas: "${output_dir}/gather-evidence.json"
        </programlisting>
        <para>The <code>model</code>, <code>max_tokens</code>,
          <code>temperature</code>, and <code>timeout_seconds</code> fields
          may all be overridden at the step level, allowing a single pipeline
          to use a fast cheap model for early steps and a slower powerful
          model only where quality is critical.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="step-function">
        <title>type: function</title>
        <para>Calls a Python function by fully qualified name. Inputs are
          passed as keyword arguments; the return value (or its fields, if a
          dict) is written to the context. This is how pipelines incorporate
          deterministic processing — loading data, parsing references,
          rendering templates, filtering results — without embedding code
          in prompts.</para>
        <programlisting language="yaml">
- name: parse_passage_reference
  type: function
  function: sp.utils.data.parse_bible_reference
  inputs:
    passage: "${passage}"
  outputs: passage_info

# passage_info.book, passage_info.chapter, etc. are now in context
        </programlisting>
        <para>Custom plugins live in a project's own <code>plugins/</code>
          directory and are referenced the same way as built-in functions.
          This is how the Ears to Hear and Discourse Flow pipelines integrate
          project-specific parsing and rendering logic without modifying the
          Scripture Pipelines engine.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="step-for-each">
        <title>type: for-each</title>
        <para>Iterates over a list — produced by an earlier step's JSON output
          or by a function — and executes a nested block of steps for each
          item. Each iteration runs in an isolated context that inherits the
          outer scope. The <code>append_to</code> directive on any inner step
          accumulates results across iterations into a named list variable in
          the outer context, enabling assembly steps to combine the results
          after the loop completes.</para>
        <programlisting language="yaml">
- name: process_each_scene
  type: for-each
  input: "${scene_list}"
  item_var: scene
  steps:
    - name: bodies
      type: llm
      prompt:
        file: prompts/bodies.gpt
        inputs:
          scene: "${scene.title}"
          text:  "${scene.greek_text}"
      outputs: bodies_content
      append_to: bodies_list    # accumulated in outer context
        </programlisting>
        <para>Nested <code>for-each</code> loops are supported, enabling
          pipelines that process, for example, every verse within every
          pericope within every book.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="step-if">
        <title>type: if</title>
        <para>Evaluates a condition expression and, when true, executes a
          nested block of steps. When false the entire block is skipped.
          This is distinct from the step-level <code>condition:</code> field
          (which skips a single step) — <code>type: if</code> guards a
          multi-step block as an atomic unit.</para>
        <programlisting language="yaml">
- name: add_cultural_notes
  type: if
  condition: "${include_culture}"
  steps:
    - name: generate_culture
      type: llm
      prompt:
        file: prompts/culture.gpt
        inputs:
          passage: "${passage}"
      outputs: cultural_notes
    - name: save_culture
      type: save
      content: "${cultural_notes}"
      saveas: "output/${passage_info.filename_prefix}_culture.md"
        </programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="variables-syntax">
      <title>Variable Resolution</title>
      <para>Scripture Pipelines uses two distinct syntaxes for variable substitution,
        each appropriate to its context.</para>
      <para>Within the YAML pipeline file, <code>${variable}</code> resolves
        values from the context map. Dot notation accesses nested fields of
        JSON objects: <code>${scene.title}</code>, <code>${passage_info.book}</code>.
        Array indexing and mapping are also supported:
        <code>${scene_list[0]}</code> and <code>${scene_list[*].title}</code>
        (which extracts all <code>title</code> fields as a flat list).
        Expressions can also be evaluated inline:
        <code>${len(results) &lt; 3}</code>.</para>
      <para>Within prompt files (<code>.gpt</code>) and Markdown templates,
        <code>{{variable}}</code> is used instead. The same dot notation and
        indexing apply. The two-syntax convention makes it immediately visible,
        when reading either a pipeline or a prompt file, which layer owns the
        substitution.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="prompt-contracts">
      <title>Prompt Contracts</title>
      <para>Each prompt file carries a YAML frontmatter header declaring the
        variables it requires and those it optionally uses. The linter validates
        that the pipeline supplies every required variable before execution begins,
        preventing runtime failures that would otherwise surface only after
        expensive preceding steps have already run.</para>
      <figure xml:id="fig-prompt-contract">
        <title>Prompt file with contract header</title>
        <programlisting>
---
requires:
  - lemma
  - evidence
optional:
  - prior_senses
---
For the lemma {{lemma}}, using the following evidence:

{{evidence}}

Produce a JSON sense inventory. For each sense, include an
"abbott_smith_audit" field listing every Abbott-Smith entry you
were given, recording whether you retained, transformed, or could
not support it with corpus evidence.
        </programlisting>
      </figure>
      <para>The audit field in the last example above is a prompt-level
        accountability contract: by requiring the LLM to enumerate its sources
        in a structured JSON field, I can verify whether the
        model actually engaged with the evidence it was provided.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="retry">
      <title>Retry Conditions</title>
      <para>Any step may declare a <code>retry</code> block specifying a
        maximum attempt count, a delay between attempts, and an optional
        condition expression. If the condition evaluates truthy after a
        successful attempt — or if the step raises an exception — the step
        re-runs up to the maximum count. This is how the Hebrew Phrasing
        pipeline handles truncated outputs: the condition checks whether the
        phrasing analysis is shorter than expected or ends mid-phrase, and
        retries with the attempt number injected into the prompt so the model
        knows it is being asked to try again.</para>
      <programlisting language="yaml">
- name: analyze_chunk
  type: llm
  prompt:
    file: prompts/phrasing.gpt
    inputs:
      chunk: "${chunk}"
      attempt: "${_retry_attempt}"
  outputs: analysis
  retry:
    max_attempts: 3
    delay_seconds: 2
    condition: "${len(analysis or '') &lt; 500}"
      </programlisting>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="iteration">
      <title>Debugging: --stop-after and --rewind-to</title>
      <para>Two CLI flags turn the pipeline into a checkpoint graph rather than
        an atomic computation. <code>--stop-after STEP</code> executes through
        the named step and halts, leaving all intermediate outputs on disk.
        <code>--rewind-to STEP</code> re-runs from the named step forward,
        reading all prior steps' outputs from disk rather than recomputing them.
        Requirements for rewinding: the step must declare <code>saveas</code>
        pointing to a single file, and that file must exist.</para>
      <para>Together these flags make the core iteration loop — inspect
        intermediate output, revise a prompt, rerun from that step — take
        seconds rather than hours even in pipelines that cost significant money
        to run from scratch. In the SemLex Greek pipeline,
        <code>--stop-after gather-evidence</code> is a standard review
        checkpoint before committing to the downstream sense-building steps.
        In Discourse Flow, <code>--stop-after segment_book</code> lets a scholar
        verify pericope boundaries before the expensive per-pericope loop
        runs.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="audit">
    <title>Structured Directory Structures and Audit Trails</title>
    <para>Scripture Pipelines pipelines save every intermediate result to the filesystem.
      Output paths are declared explicitly in each step's <code>saveas</code>
      field, and Scripture Pipelines creates the necessary directory structure
      automatically.</para>
    <para>For a Greek lexicon, a flat output directory is unworkable at scale:
      the UTF-8 sort order of Greek lemmas groups entries in ways that make
      navigation difficult, and a single directory with thousands of files
      is unwieldy. Scripture Pipelines' <code>saveas</code> field accepts a
      <code>group_by_prefix: 2</code> option that inserts a subdirectory
      named after the first two characters of the lemma — using the actual
      Greek Unicode characters — before the lemma's own files. The SemLex
      Greek pipeline uses this throughout:</para>
    <programlisting language="yaml">
saveas:
  path: "${output_dir}/intermediate/${row.lemma}.structure.json"
  group_by_prefix: 2
    </programlisting>
    <para>This produces a tree keyed on the Greek characters themselves:</para>
    <programlisting>
obsidian/grc/intermediate/
  ἀγ/
    ἀγαπάω.raw.xml
    ἀγαπάω.structure.json
    ἀγαπάω.semantic.json
    ἀγαπάω.withexamples.md
    ἀγγέλλω.raw.xml
    ...
  ἀδ/
    ἀδελφός.structure.json
    ...
  πι/
    πιστεύω.raw.xml
    πιστεύω.structure.json
    ...
    </programlisting>
    <para>Each lemma's full multi-pass output — raw evidence, enhanced
      analysis, citation verification, sense structure, final formatted
      entry — lives together under its prefix directory. This makes it
      natural to open any lemma's folder in an editor or Obsidian vault
      and inspect exactly what each pipeline pass produced, in the
      sequence it was produced. The directory tree is also the audit trail:
      committed to version control, it records the provenance of every
      generated artifact and makes the full history of a lemma's
      development inspectable by any collaborator.</para>
    <para>This persistence strategy has several further benefits. Failures
      are cheap: if any pass produces unsatisfactory output, only that step
      needs to be rerun; all prior outputs remain on disk. Any intermediate
      file can be opened and examined before downstream steps consume it —
      or handed to an LLM with the instruction to audit whether it correctly
      reflects the inputs from the preceding step. When something looks wrong
      in a final lexicon entry, I can read backward through
      the saved files to identify which pass introduced the problem.</para>

    <section xml:id="audit-step-grounding">
      <title>Finding Where the Chain Breaks: AI-Assisted Grounding Audits</title>
      <para>The most damaging pipeline failure is not malformed JSON or a
        missing field — it is a step that received its inputs and produced
        a structurally valid output that does not reflect what it was given.
        A step that generates study questions about a passage but ignores the
        exegetical analysis from the preceding step; a step that receives a
        scene list but generates generic content independent of scene
        structure; a step that accumulates entity data and gives it negligible
        weight in its response. These failures pass schema validation. They
        are visible only as content problems to a reader who knows what the
        intermediate data should have contributed.</para>
      <para>Because all intermediate outputs are persisted to disk, the
        auditing workflow is tractable. Given two consecutive intermediate
        files — step N-1's output and step N's output — an LLM can be asked
        directly: does step N's output reflect the content of step N-1? Are
        the specific features, entities, or analytical conclusions from
        step N-1 visible in what step N produced? If not, which are absent,
        and where would you expect to find them? This audit can be applied at
        any step boundary, in either direction: forward from a suspect input
        toward its consumers, or backward from a poor final output toward
        the earliest step whose output is adequate.</para>
      <para>The standard approach when something looks wrong in a final
        output is to work backward through the saved intermediate files.
        At each step boundary, the adjacent intermediate files are given
        to an LLM for a grounding audit. The first boundary where the audit
        finds missing grounding is where the prompt needs revision — not
        the final step, which is often the visible surface of a failure
        that originates earlier. <code>--stop-after STEP</code> runs the
        pipeline to a checkpoint and halts; after identifying the failing
        step, <code>--rewind-to STEP</code> reruns from that prompt forward
        once it is revised. The cost of a revision iteration is one step
        forward, not a full pipeline rerun.</para>
      <para>This technique depends on design decisions made at construction
        time. Prompts that explicitly instruct the model to account for each
        named input invite scrutiny; prompts that pass large context blocks
        without specifying how they should be used give the model latitude
        to underweight them silently. Adding grounding accountability fields
        to intermediate JSON schemas — fields that require the model to
        enumerate which features of a prior step's output it drew on, and
        why — converts this failure mode from invisible to detectable. When
        the field is absent or sparse, the output is suspect. The same
        accountability pattern that the SemLex Abbott-Smith audit uses for
        source enumeration applies at the inter-step level: making grounding
        explicit in the schema turns a silent pipeline failure into a
        checkable contract.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="audit-identifier-consistency">
      <title>Identifier Consistency: A Persistent Debugging Problem</title>
      <para>A specific failure mode that recurs across all Scripture Pipelines
        projects is identifier inconsistency: a key produced in one step does
        not match the form expected by a later step that tries to look it up,
        join on it, or use it as a filename. The failure is frequently silent.
        The later step receives an empty result or a missing file, may produce
        no output, and continues — leaving nothing in the intermediate files
        except the absence of what should have been there. Schema validation
        cannot catch it; input and output are both structurally valid.
        The symptom appears as thin or missing content in the final output,
        and tracing it back to a key mismatch several steps earlier takes
        time proportional to how many steps the mismatch has silently
        propagated through.</para>
      <para>The cases that have occurred in practice span several
        categories:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Passage reference forms.</emphasis>
          A pipeline uses the passage <code>Mark 10:46-52</code> as an entry
          point. One step normalizes it to a filename prefix
          <code>mark-10-46-52</code>; a later step, written independently,
          constructs the lookup key as <code>MRK_10_46</code> from the
          USFM book code. Two keys for the same passage that are
          generated independently in different steps never match. The full
          Paratext and USFM ecosystem uses several different book code
          conventions — <code>MRK</code>, <code>Mrk</code>,
          <code>Mark</code>, <code>mr</code> — that collide across
          data sources.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Scene identifiers generated by an
          LLM.</emphasis> A step produces a scene list in which scene IDs
          are LLM-generated strings: <code>"Scene 1: Bartimaeus by the
          Roadside"</code>. A subsequent step iterates over this list and
          writes one intermediate file per scene, using the scene ID as the
          filename stem. The file is written as
          <code>scene-1-bartimaeus-by-the-roadside.json</code>. A third step
          reads the scene file by constructing the path from the scene ID
          stored in the context. If the normalization function in step two
          differs from the one in step three by any detail — case, whitespace
          handling, truncation of long titles — no file is found and the
          step produces empty output. If the steps were written in different
          sessions, the divergence may not be noticed until a passage with
          a long scene title triggers the truncation case for the first
          time.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Lemma Unicode normalization.</emphasis>
          Greek lemma strings may arrive from different data sources in
          different Unicode normalization forms, or with different
          accentuation conventions for the same lexical form. Abbott-Smith
          entries, SBLGNT word data, and the Macula Greek lemma column follow
          different conventions at the edges. A join on lemma string that
          works for the 500 most frequent lemmas fails silently for less
          common forms with precomposed vs. decomposed diacritics or
          aspirate/smooth breathing differences.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Entity and word IDs across datasets.</emphasis>
          ACAI entity records are anchored to Macula node IDs; the
          Levinsohn LGNTDF annotations use word-level indexes in their
          own sequence. A step that tries to join Levinsohn features with
          ACAI entity occurrences needs a shared anchor that both datasets
          use. If the join key is constructed differently in two plugin
          functions written independently, the join produces an empty result
          that no schema check catches.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The design rule that has proven most effective is: never use
        an LLM-generated string as a join key or filename. LLMs produce
        natural language labels; normalization to canonical identifiers must
        happen in a deterministic function step that is versioned and
        testable. The <code>plugins/</code> directory in each project
        contains normalization utilities — <code>scene_id_normalize()</code>,
        <code>passage_key()</code>, <code>lemma_normalize()</code> — that
        are the single canonical transformation from input string to stable
        key. All steps that produce or consume a given key form call the
        same function. When the normalization rule changes, one function
        changes and the mismatch surface collapses to a single version.</para>
      <para>Intermediate JSON files are the detection layer. Each scene
        entry stores both the human-readable label (for display and audit)
        and the normalized ID (for all downstream use). When an ID mismatch
        is suspected, <code>--stop-after</code> at the producing step lets
        the author inspect which IDs were written and compare them against
        the IDs the consuming step would construct — before the consuming
        step has executed and produced empty output. Catching the mismatch
        at the producing step costs one rewind; catching it after three
        downstream steps have silently propagated the empty result costs
        four. The discipline of reading intermediate files before
        building on them is the same discipline required for grounding
        audits; identifier consistency and content grounding are both
        visible in the same files, at the same checkpoint.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="audit-prompt-organization">
      <title>Prompt Organization for Dual-Audience Readability</title>
      <para>LLM prompts are unique technical documents: they must be simultaneously
        readable by humans (for verification, maintenance, and debugging) and by AI
        systems (for accurate task execution). Like XML schema documentation—which must
        be both human-readable prose and machine-processable constraint definitions—prompts
        encode both the transformation rules and examples demonstrating those rules. Poor
        organization creates cognitive overload for both audiences.</para>

      <para>Working with AI in production environments, the danger of humans and AIs
        getting overwhelmed by data and chasing tangents is very high. A 500-line prompt
        processing biblical passages with 50+ input fields and complex transformation
        rules is not a toy example—it is a specification document where both audiences
        must find what they need quickly or fail. Good results require deliberate design
        and infrastructure to overcome this cognitive load.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">YAML Frontmatter</emphasis> — Machine-readable
          metadata (required/optional inputs, output format)</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">WHAT THIS PROMPT PRODUCES</emphasis> — Purpose
          statement and conceptual model for both audiences</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">OUTPUT FORMAT</emphasis> — JSON schema with
          wording guidelines</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">TASK SECTIONS</emphasis> — Each major
          transformation gets its own complete section containing:
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Input: Where to Find the Data</emphasis> — Explicit
              field mappings preventing hallucination</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Transformation Rules</emphasis> — With ✅/❌ examples
              showing correct/incorrect patterns</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Examples: Input → Transformation → Output</emphasis> —
              Complete worked examples (with TODOs for manual completion)</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis>Rules Specific to This Output Type</emphasis> —
              Task-specific constraints</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para></listitem>

        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">COVERAGE &amp; QUALITY CHECKLIST</emphasis> —
          Pre-submission verification for AI self-checking</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">INPUT DATA</emphasis> — Template variable
          instantiation</para></listitem>

        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">CRITICAL REMINDERS</emphasis> — Final
          guardrails</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <section xml:id="cognitive-load-reduction">
        <title>Reducing Cognitive Load: Information Scent and Locality of Reference</title>

        <para>The cognitive science principle of <emphasis>locality of reference</emphasis>—that
          related information should be physically proximate—applies equally to both human
          and AI readers. When a programmer searches for "the rule about Notice questions,"
          they should find everything about Notice questions in one section. When an AI
          encounters transformation rules, it should find the input data sources and examples
          in the same context window, not 300 lines away.</para>

        <para><emphasis>Information scent</emphasis>—the ability to predict where to find
          specific information—determines whether a prompt is maintainable at scale. Can you
          predict where the rule about background usage will be? (In the section about Imagine
          questions, where background is used.) Can you predict where the data source for
          <code>treasure_verb</code> is documented? (In the Input subsection of the Hearts
          section, where that field is generated.) When scent fails—when rules are scattered,
          examples are separated from what they exemplify, or data sources are mentioned once
          in a different section—both humans and AIs waste cognitive resources searching
          rather than understanding.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">For Humans:</emphasis></para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Locality of reference</emphasis>: Everything about
            "Notice questions" lives in the Notice section. No searching across 500+ lines
            for scattered rules. A human debugging a problem can open the relevant section
            and see the complete specification: what data is available, what transformation
            is required, what the output should look like, and what the constraints are.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Verifiable transformation</emphasis>: Given this input
            data, following these rules, we expect this output. Debugging failures becomes
            systematic. The input-rules-output co-location makes it possible to trace from
            a bad output back to either insufficient input data or misapplied rules.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Explicit data grounding</emphasis>: "This output field
            comes from <code>verses.heart_movements[].treasure_verb</code>" prevents AI from
            fabricating content and makes human review feasible. A reviewer can verify that
            every output field has a documented source.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">For AI:</emphasis></para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Co-located context</emphasis>: Rules, examples, and data
            sources appear together in the context window. Like XML schema documentation where
            the constraint definition, prose explanation, and usage examples are proximate,
            prompts that co-locate these elements reduce the AI's need to "remember" that the
            data source was mentioned 200 lines earlier. In production prompts processing
            hundreds of verses with dozens of fields, context window management is not
            theoretical—it determines whether the AI can maintain coherent understanding
            across the full specification.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Progressive refinement</emphasis>: The structure mirrors
            the AI's processing: What am I making? → How do I format it? → What data do I
            have? → How do I transform it? → What are the constraints? This sequencing
            prevents the AI from chasing tangents by establishing the output structure before
            introducing the input data.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Example-rule alignment</emphasis>: Transformation rules
            immediately followed by examples that demonstrate those rules creates
            reinforcement without requiring the AI to associate scattered examples with
            abstract rules stated elsewhere. This is the prompt equivalent of XML schema's
            inline annotations—the explanation appears precisely where it is needed.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The parallel to XML schema documentation is instructive: both are formal
          specifications that must be machine-processable while remaining human-readable.
          Both succeed when structure makes information predictable. A well-organized XML
          schema lets a developer predict where to find the constraints for a particular
          element. A well-organized prompt lets both programmer and AI predict where to find
          the data source, transformation rules, and examples for a particular output field.
          The markup differs, but the information architecture principle is identical.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="audit-infrastructure-for-prompts">
        <title>Audit Infrastructure for Prompt Quality</title>
        <para>The audit skill enforces three principles essential for production quality:</para>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Input Data Grounding (Prevents
            Hallucination)</emphasis>: Every output field must have a documented input
            source. "Generate questions about what characters treasure" is ungrounded.
            "<code>heart_aspect</code> field must use <code>treasure_verb</code> from
            <code>verses.heart_movements[]</code> where <code>certainty</code> is high"
            is grounded. The audit verifies this mapping exists.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Example Diversity (Prevents
            Overfitting)</emphasis>: Examples from a single passage train the AI on
            specifics, not patterns. The audit counts distinct passages and narrative
            types, flagging single-source examples.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">AI-Generated Example Detection (#1 Source
            of Problems)</emphasis>: Nothing produced by an LLM can be used as training
            data in prompts. AI-generated examples encode patterns the AI already knows,
            not the precise pattern the human intends. The audit compares current version
            with last commit, flagging ANY new examples for human review. This breaks the
            feedback loop where AI output becomes AI input, preventing drift from
            intent.</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="measured-impact">
        <title>Measured Impact in Production Use</title>
        <para>These are not toy examples. The prompts under discussion generate Bible
          study questions from passages in Mark, Psalms, Genesis, and Ruth—processing
          verse-level data enriched with sensory details, cultural background, character
          heart movements, and narrative structure annotations. A single passage may
          involve 50+ input fields across multiple JSON files. Without deliberate
          organization to combat cognitive overload, both humans and AIs get lost in
          the data.</para>

        <para>Measured results from reorganizing production prompts:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Human maintenance time</emphasis>: Reorganizing from
            scattered to task-focused structure reduced "find the relevant rule" time from
            approximately 5 minutes to approximately 30 seconds. When a prompt fails on
            Psalm 23, the developer can locate the relevant section in seconds rather than
            re-reading 500 lines searching for scattered rules.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>AI consistency</emphasis>: Co-locating data sources with
            transformation rules reduced field-source mismatches from approximately 15% to
            approximately 2% (measured over 50 passages across multiple books and genres).
            The AI stopped fabricating content when the data source was visible in the same
            section as the transformation rule.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Example quality</emphasis>: Blocking AI-generated examples
            and requiring human-written examples eliminated approximately 40% of subtle
            pattern violations that passed initial review. AI-generated examples looked
            plausible but encoded the wrong pattern; human examples demonstrated the
            precise behavior required.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>These results suggest that prompts benefit from the same information
          architecture principles that make technical documentation effective: locality
          of reference, explicit data flow, worked examples, and human authorship of
          training data. The task-focused organization serves both human understanding
          and AI execution by reducing cognitive load through careful information
          structure. In production environments where prompts process real data at scale,
          organization is not cosmetic—it determines whether the system produces reliable
          results or descends into hallucination and inconsistency.</para>

        <para>The success of this organization pattern in production use led to its
          formalization as a global LLMFlow convention with automated audit tooling.
          After battle-testing the structure on 15+ prompts ranging from 117 to 603
          lines across multiple biblical books and genres, the pattern proved robust
          enough to encode as a standard. The audit skill—a read-only workflow tool
          that checks for convention compliance, input data grounding, example
          diversity, and AI-generated example pollution—now systematically detects
          the problems that previously required manual review. This combination of
          structured organization and automated verification measurably improves both
          LLM performance (by reducing hallucination through explicit data grounding)
          and human oversight (by making debugging systematic rather than exploratory).
          The convention and audit tooling are proposed as global LLMFlow resources
          available to all projects. Our real-world
          experience demonstrates that prompt organization is architecture, not
          formatting—it shapes whether AI collaboration produces reliable results or
          degenerates into maintenance burden.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="development-workflow">
    <title>AI-Assisted Development: Context, Workflow, and Staying in Sync</title>
    <para>A persistent challenge when using LLMs as development collaborators is
      keeping the model oriented: knowing which repository it is in, what the
      pipeline language looks like, what work is in progress, and what it should
      not touch. Without explicit scaffolding, each conversation starts from
      scratch — or worse, the model invents plausible-looking but wrong answers
      because it lacks project-specific context.</para>
    <para><code>sp init</code> addresses this directly by scaffolding a set
      of AI context files alongside the pipeline and prompt starter files:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><code>docs/ai-context/overview.md</code> — project
        description, directory layout, and canonical references, loaded
        automatically by GitHub Copilot at the start of every session</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><code>docs/ai-context/rules.md</code> — guardrails for
        AI collaborators: respect the YAML schema, keep prompts and pipelines
        in sync, preserve human editorial ownership of outputs</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><code>docs/ai-context/index.md</code> — a topic-to-document
        routing table so the model knows which reference to consult for each
        class of question, rather than paraphrasing from training data</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><code>docs/spl-quickref.md</code> — the
        Scripture Pipelines language in compact form, always available in the project's own
        docs so the model understands the pipeline language without needing the
        upstream engine repository in scope</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para><code>.github/copilot-instructions.md</code> — session
        start instructions: read <code>project/TODO.md</code> first, explain
        before implementing, lint and dry-run before executing, link issues
        from <code>project/TODO.md</code>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><code>project/TODO.md</code> — the live task list with
        active work, backlog, and done items; the AI reads this at session
        start to know the current state of the project</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The copilot instructions and AI context together solve a practical
      synchronization problem: the LLM understands what YAML keys are valid,
      what the prompt contract syntax looks like, and what work is in flight —
      without my needing to explain any of it at the start of each
      session. Because the AI context files are in the project repository and
      committed to version control, they stay in sync with the pipelines and
      prompts they describe. When the pipeline language gains a new step type
      or the project priorities shift, updating the AI context is a first-class
      development task, not an afterthought.</para>
    <para>Maintaining an AI context directory introduces its own engineering discipline.
      Volume and organization affect model behavior in measurable ways. Large language
      models exhibit a "lost in the middle" effect: content near the beginning and end of a
      long input is weighted more heavily than content in the middle, regardless of
      relevance. Irrelevant context is not neutral — it actively competes with signal, making
      the model less likely to surface the relevant portion than if only the relevant text
      had been provided. A sprawling context file that accumulates every fact about a
      project will degrade the quality of answers involving only a small corner of
      it.</para>
    <para>The <code>docs/ai-context/index.md</code> routing table addresses
      this directly: rather than loading all context files at once,
      the model is instructed to read only the file that covers the
      specific question at hand. Each context file opens with two lines that
      cannot be skipped: a "use this file for" trigger that identifies the
      topics it covers, and a size budget — for example,
      <quote>Budget: 150 lines / 5KB. If adding content would push past this,
      split into a new file and add a row to <code>index.md</code>.</quote>
      The budget line serves a second purpose: it tells any future contributor,
      human or AI, exactly what to do when a file grows too large, rather than
      leaving that decision to accumulate silently across sessions.</para>
    <para>The same logic that governs prose documentation
      applies here. Tables are preferable to prose for lookup-oriented
      content; brief declarative bullets outperform explanatory paragraphs;
      and tutorial material belongs in <code>docs/</code> rather than
      in the AI context directory. The AI context files are not documentation
      for human readers — they are a precision instrument tuned to a specific
      retrieval task, and they should be maintained as such.</para>

    <section xml:id="tdd-workflow">
      <title>Test-Driven Development and the Issue Lifecycle</title>
      <para>Scripture Pipelines' own engine is developed test-first, and the same discipline
        applies to resource repositories. The standard workflow for any
        meaningful change:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>Review the project board; pick the highest-priority open
          issue</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Write a failing test that specifies the expected
          behavior — for a pipeline change, this means asserting on the
          structure of intermediate JSON or on context variable values after
          the step runs</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Implement until the test passes</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Run the full test suite to confirm no regressions</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>Commit with a message that references the issue number;
          close the issue</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>The LLM collaborator participates in every step. Because
        <code>.github/copilot-instructions.md</code> instructs it to explain
        before implementing, to lint pipelines before running them, and to
        reference issues from <code>project/TODO.md</code>, the model operates
        as an informed contributor rather than an autonomous agent. I am
        the architect and the one who holds the critical domain knowledge the
        model does not have: which datasets exist and are trustworthy, what the
        project is trying to accomplish, which approaches will work for this
        community, and what the output must ultimately be. The model implements
        what I specify and handles the mechanical work of drafting tests,
        running lint cycles, and wiring pipeline steps. The result is a TDD
        discipline maintained across sessions because the AI context enforces
        it — but the constraints in that context are entirely my
        contribution.</para>
      <para>The issue tracker serves a third role beyond backlog management
        and upstream bug reporting: it is the live design forum. When a
        feature is complex enough that the right approach is not obvious, the
        design conversation belongs in an issue thread, not in a document
        that must be kept in sync. In the Discourse Flow nested pericope work,
        issue #3 captures the <emphasis>what</emphasis> — the rhetorical case
        for nested pericopes, the proposed schema, the triggering conditions —
        while issue #5 was opened specifically to carry the
        <emphasis>how</emphasis>: the two-pass pipeline design, the new
        prompt contract, the checkpoint implications. Design decisions and
        their rationale are recorded as comments as the thread evolves. The
        entire trajectory from initial proposal through two design revisions
        is preserved in the issue thread, not in a design document that might
        drift out of sync with the implementation. When implementation begins,
        <code>project/TODO.md</code> links to both issues; when it is complete,
        the issues are closed with commit references. The issue tracker is not
        only where completed work is recorded — it is where in-progress
        thinking is visible and revisable before any code is touched.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="collaboration-texture">
      <title>What Is Easy and What Takes Work</title>
      <para>Working with an AI development collaborator across the projects
        described in this paper has clarified what the tool offloads and
        what it cannot replace. The distinction shapes how sessions are
        structured and where my attention must be
        concentrated.</para>
      <para>Format conversion is never where the intellectual work lives.
        Given a clear intermediate JSON schema and a target format — USX 3.1,
        Markdown, a TSV manifest — the AI produces a correct rendering step
        on a first or second attempt. The function step that maps JSON scene
        fields to USX <code>&lt;para&gt;</code> elements with the right USFM
        style codes, the Markdown template that formats a lexicon entry's
        senses and citations, the plugin that extracts verse-range text from
        a local USFM file: all of these are mechanical from a precise
        description. The question "how do I convert this JSON to USX?" simply
        does not consume time once shared identifiers are in place. The same
        is true of pipeline scaffolding: defining step names, wiring outputs
        to inputs, writing prompt contract headers, implementing retry
        conditions. If the pipeline steps are clearly described, the AI
        assembles the skeleton correctly. These are tasks the tool handles;
        they are not where scholarly judgment is applied.</para>
      <para>The decisions that require sustained intellectual engagement are
        qualitatively different:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Choosing and structuring data
          sources.</emphasis> Which dataset to use at each step, what subset
          is relevant, and how to structure it as prompt input is not
          mechanical. Deciding that Levinsohn LGNTDF annotations should be
          presented to the segmentation step indexed by verse and grouped by
          feature type — rather than as a flat token stream — requires
          understanding both the dataset's structure and the segmentation task
          deeply enough to know what structural signal the model must be led
          to notice. The AI implements whatever structure is specified;
          specifying it correctly to get the analytical result I want is my work.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Designing accountability
          fields.</emphasis> Which aspects of the LLM's reasoning to make
          explicit in intermediate JSON — which sources to require
          enumeration of, which judgments to require justification for —
          is an epistemological decision. Deciding that the SemLex
          gather-evidence step must name every Abbott-Smith sense it was
          given and record whether each was retained or rejected with a
          reason makes a quality claim about what the lexicon should be
          accountable to. No tool makes that claim on the lexicographer's
          behalf.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Defining what "good" means.</emphasis>
          For every step that produces human-facing output, quality criteria
          must be specified precisely enough that a domain scholar or focus
          group can evaluate a pass or fail. What makes a Connecting question
          genuinely grounded in textual tension rather than generically
          moralistic? What makes a pericope segmentation defensible? These
          criteria can be written into context files and prompt instructions
          — but they must first be worked out by practitioners who know the
          material.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>The explanation phase as error
          prevention.</emphasis> The discipline of requiring the AI to explain
          what it is about to do, in full, before touching any file reliably
          surfaces misunderstandings that would otherwise become incorrect
          implementations. In the hebrew-phrasing project, it caught a
          suffix-gloss fix script that would have applied the wrong pronoun
          form for hundreds of rows before a line of code was written. In Ears
          to Hear, it surfaced a misunderstanding about whether a scene-id
          normalization function should operate on the raw LLM string output
          or the parsed AST. In both cases the problem was visible in the
          explanation paragraph. The discipline works because explanation
          commits the model to a specific interpretation — and a committed
          interpretation can be evaluated before any file is modified.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Recognizing which computations are
          stable.</emphasis> AI collaborators readily propose uniform designs
          — data structures where all outputs use the same identity key,
          pipelines where every step depends on the same computed artifact.
          My advantage is understanding which computations are stable
          and which are not: which outputs represent ground truth inherent in
          the source text (a verse reference exists independently of any
          analysis) and which represent conclusions the pipeline computed (a
          scene boundary is where we decided to put it, and we may decide
          differently next month when upstream discourse data improves).</para>
          <para>In the Ears to Hear enrichment pipeline, the initial design
          proposal keyed every enrichment result — background items, heart
          movements, layer2 interpretations, narrator signals — by the
          LLM-produced scene identifier. I interrupted it with a question:
          <quote>Some of these things could depend on the
          verse, not the scene. If the scene boundaries change, a lot of
          other things could be stable — are you sure you want everything to
          depend on our computed scenes?</quote> The AI worked through it
          field by field and arrived at a different design: a
          <code>verse-atlas</code> keyed by verse reference (stable; survives
          any future re-segmentation, because verse references are ground
          truth in the source text) and a <code>scene-synthesis</code> keyed
          by scene (cheap to rerun when scenes change, because the expensive
          verse-level exegetical work has already been preserved).</para>
          <para>Neither output structure nor the distinction between them
          required knowledge the AI did not have. What was required was
          recognizing that the two artifacts had different durability
          requirements — a judgment about the pipeline's own lifecycle that
          only I could make, knowing the planned upstream changes.
          The redesign took one exchange. The original design would
          have caused expensive rework the first time scene boundaries were
          revised. This pattern — seeing the time dimension of the
          design, recognizing that one layer is load-bearing and volatile, and
          redirecting before any code is written — recurs across all Scripture
          Pipelines projects and is not detectable by any automated check.
          I am the one who knows the project will still be running
          in six months.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Catching a metric that looks like a
          content judgment but isn't.</emphasis> The Discourse Flow nested
          pericope feature (issue #3) triggered a discussion about what
          condition should cause a pericope to be subdivided in a second
          analysis pass. The initial proposal was a verse-count threshold:
          subdivide any pericope exceeding N verses. This is a pipeline-level
          number and straightforward to implement. The question I asked was:
          what is the threshold actually a proxy for? In this case, the answer
          was already in the pipeline's own output. The <code>segment_book</code>
          step, as instructed, already records why each sub-threshold signal was
          considered but not elevated to a boundary — the reasoning is present
          in the <code>boundary_rationale</code> prose. A verse count threshold
          would have subdivided long pericopes that were rhetorically unified
          and left short pericopes with genuine internal cast or setting shifts
          untouched. The right trigger was a new structured field —
          <code>internal_subdivision_signals</code> — that asked the
          segmentation pass to collect those subordinated signals explicitly.
          If the array is non-empty, a subdivision candidate exists; if not,
          the pericope is left flat regardless of its verse span. The AI
          implemented the correct design in a single exchange once the question
          was framed correctly. Framing it correctly required recognizing that
          verse count and discourse signal presence are different kinds of thing
          — a judgment about what the pipeline is actually measuring that no
          automated check surfaces.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>The sessions producing the case studies described in this paper
        used GitHub Copilot running on Claude Sonnet as the development
        collaborator throughout — the same model cited in the
        hebrew-phrasing subsection below. The workflow described here is
        not an idealization; it is a description of actual practice. The
        <code>project/TODO.md</code> file functions literally as session
        state: it carries the task in progress, blocked items with their
        blockers, and completed items with their git commit hashes. A session
        begins with the AI reading the TODO and confirming what it is working
        on; it ends with the change committed and the done record written.
        In between, I architect the solution. Not just specifying
        what to implement, but bringing knowledge the AI does not have: that
        Levinsohn's discourse annotations exist and are the right foundation
        for pericope segmentation; that a particular fix script needs to
        distinguish possessive from object pronouns based on the preceding
        token's grammatical class; that a proposed approach to scene-id
        normalization will break downstream rendering in a way that only
        someone who knows the full output pipeline can anticipate. The
        explanation phase catches the cases where the AI's interpretation
        diverges from what I intended; I then correct it,
        often because I know something critical that was never
        written down. The <code>copilot-instructions.md</code> is not
        documentation — it is the active working memory and constraint system
        that makes the collaboration trustworthy across the many sessions a
        project requires. But the vision encoded in those constraints, and
        the judgment that shaped them, are entirely mine.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="data-sources">
    <title>Scholarly Data Sources</title>
    <para>Pipeline steps are only as good as the data they can access.
      Before examining the specific datasets that current Scripture Pipelines
      projects draw on, it is useful to distinguish the access patterns
      available and when each is the right choice. The Nida Institute
      projects described here use all four.</para>

    <section xml:id="ds-access-patterns">
      <title>Data Access Patterns</title>
      <para>Four structurally distinct patterns are available for bringing
        data into a pipeline step. The choice among them is a design
        decision: it determines reproducibility, infrastructure requirements,
        and how much retrieval reasoning the model is asked to contribute.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Filesystem files from version-controlled
          repositories.</emphasis> The most common pattern in current
          projects. Macula Hebrew TSV data, the Levinsohn LGNTDF dataset,
          ACAI entity JSON, and source transcriptions all enter pipelines
          through <code>type: function</code> or <code>type: tsv</code>
          steps that read a local file path, filter by passage reference or
          entity key, and return structured data to the pipeline context.
          Appropriate when the dataset is stable, versioned, and small
          enough to clone. A pipeline that draws only on local files is
          fully deterministic: any collaborator with the same clones runs
          identically, and the data version is recoverable from the upstream
          repository's git history. No running server, no authentication,
          no API quota.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Database queries (BaseX or
          similar).</emphasis> The right pattern when data is large,
          structured as XML, and requires principled subset selection. The
          planned <code>type: xquery</code> step executes XQuery expressions
          against a BaseX database — the natural fit for the full Macula
          corpora, syntactic treebanks, and lexicon collections. Appropriate
          when the retrieval question is structural: all occurrences of a
          grammatical construction across the Pauline epistles; all tokens in
          a passage with their treebank parent relationships; all lexicon
          entries in a semantic domain. These queries can be approximated
          with file-loading filters, but XQuery expresses them precisely and
          the query itself lives in the pipeline as part of its data
          transformation record. A <code>--stop-after</code> at the query
          step lets the author inspect the returned data and refine the
          query before any expensive LLM step downstream executes.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>MCP (Model Context Protocol).</emphasis>
          The right pattern when data retrieval is itself a reasoning task —
          when what to fetch depends on what the model is processing, not on
          a fixed reference. In the Ears to Hear pipeline, the
          <code>enrich_passage</code> step gives the LLM access to MCP
          tools: it fetches passage text, then looks up entities it
          encounters, then retrieves word-sense data for terms it judges
          significant — potentially 40 tool calls within a single LLM step.
          The model decides the retrieval sequence; the pipeline declares
          only which MCP server to connect to. Appropriate when the relevant
          data subset is not known until the model is reasoning about the
          content, or when the data source is dynamic or externally managed.
          The cost is indeterminism: two runs may follow different tool-call
          chains. The structured JSON capturing the enrichment output records
          what was actually fetched, restoring auditability downstream. MCP
          should be reserved for steps where reasoning-driven retrieval
          genuinely adds value; static lookups belong in deterministic
          function steps.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Pipeline context data.</emphasis> The
          flow of outputs between steps within the pipeline itself. Every
          step that declares <code>outputs: some_variable</code> makes its
          result available downstream via <code>${some_variable}</code>.
          This is the default data-flow mechanism, and it requires a
          specific discipline: it is straightforward to write a prompt that
          nominally <emphasis>receives</emphasis> a variable but gives it
          little weight against the surrounding context, or where the
          instructions do not tell the model how to relate the variable
          to the task. A step that receives earlier pipeline outputs but
          fails to ground its response in them is one of the most common
          silent pipeline failures — and the subject of the AI-assisted
          grounding audit technique described in the previous
          section.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="ds-current">
      <title>Datasets Used in Ears to Hear</title>
      <para>The Ears to Hear case study draws on multiple scholarly datasets,
        accessed through a combination of <code>type: function</code> steps,
        <code>type: tsv</code> steps, and MCP tool calls. The following
        datasets are used across the book summary, discourse analysis, and
        leaders' guide pipelines:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Macula Greek</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-macula-greek"/>
          (Clear-Bible / unfoldingWord): Morphologically annotated Greek New
          Testament with syntactic treebanks. Includes lemma, gloss, part of
          speech, person/gender/number, case, and full dependency syntax trees.
          Accessed via MCP tools (<code>get_word_info</code>,
          <code>get_word_sense</code>) in narrative enrichment, and directly
          via JSON files in book-level synthesis. The Ears to Hear pipelines
          primarily use the morphological and lexical layers; the syntax trees,
          while available in the same dataset, are used more extensively in
          other Scripture Pipelines projects.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>ACAI (Ancient Chains of Annotation Integration)</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-acai"/>
          (Rick Brannan / Mission Mutual, CC BY-SA 4.0): Biblical entity
          annotations covering people, places, flora, fauna, deities, groups,
          realia (e.g., <code>realia:Denarius</code>), and keyterms. Anchored
          to Macula node IDs, allowing precise verse-range lookup. Accessed both
          via MCP tools (<code>get_acai_entities_for_passage</code>,
          <code>get_acai_entity_detail</code>) and via local JSON files with a
          book-specific index. Used in narrative enrichment, book summaries, and
          scene synthesis to identify participants, cultural objects, and
          geographic context.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Levinsohn LGNTDF</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-lgntdf"/>
          (Steven H. Levinsohn, Biblical Humanities): Word-level discourse feature
          annotations for the Greek New Testament encoding Levinsohn's discourse
          grammar categories — cataphoric focus markers, point-of-departure
          shifts, vocatives, boundary markers, and connective particles. For 1
          John alone this dataset contains 806 word-level annotations. Used
          upstream in the Discourse Flow (Greek NT) pipeline for pericope
          segmentation; Ears to Hear consumes the resulting scene boundaries and
          discourse structures indirectly through the scene-overlay JSON produced
          by Discourse Flow.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Levinsohn &amp; Samuel HOTDF</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-hotdf"/>
          (Steven H. Levinsohn and David Samuel): Word-level discourse feature
          annotations for the Hebrew Old Testament, encoding similar discourse
          grammar categories (end-dislocation, continuation, ellipsis, DFE
          markers). Used upstream in the Discourse Flow Hebrew pipeline for
          pericope segmentation in Hebrew Bible projects. Like LGNTDF for the
          Greek New Testament, this dataset provides the scholarly foundation
          for discourse-aware scene boundaries, preventing the LLM from imposing
          arbitrary chapter divisions on narratives that cross traditional
          boundaries.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>SBLGNT</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-sblgnt"/>
          (Society of Biblical Literature Greek New Testament): The base Greek text for all Greek
          New Testament pipelines, accessed via the pipeline
          <code>source: SBLGNT</code> variable and resolved by a built-in Bible
          reference function step, or fetched via MCP
          (<code>get_passage_text</code>).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Additional datasets are used in other Scripture Pipelines projects:
        Macula Hebrew <xref linkend="ref-macula-hebrew"/> and MorphHB <xref linkend="ref-morphhb"/> for Hebrew Phrasing, SDBH <xref linkend="ref-sdbh"/> for lexical work,
        and the full catalog of 20+ datasets is maintained in the dataset
        registry <xref linkend="ref-awesome-biblical-data"/>. The Discourse Flow pipelines (both Greek NT and Hebrew OT),
        which apply Levinsohn's discourse grammar framework <xref linkend="ref-levinsohn-book"/> to identify pericope boundaries, are
        foundational dependencies for projects like Ears to Hear that require
        discourse-aware segmentation as input.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="ds-integrations">
      <title>Data Source Integration Architecture</title>
      <para>Scripture Pipelines integrates structured scholarly datasets through
        two mechanisms: format-specific step types for external systems, and a
        dataset registry for automatic discovery and local caching.</para>

      <section xml:id="ds-systems">
        <title>Supported Systems and Formats</title>
        <para>The following systems and formats are currently supported:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Paratext projects and Scripture Burrito
            packages</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-usfm"/> <xref linkend="ref-scripture-burrito"/>: Scripture source utilities allow pipelines to
            read any translation or back-translation stored in a local Paratext
            installation or Scripture Burrito bundle — USFM 3.1 and USX 3.1
            formats — and present it as a structured verse-range input. This
            means a pipeline can be run against any translation in a Paratext
            project directory without manual export: back-translation checks,
            discourse analyses, and leaders' guide pipelines all become
            immediately applicable to local translation work in progress.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>BaseX XML database queries</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-basex"/>: A
            <code>type: xquery</code> step type allows pipelines to query
            BaseX XML databases containing Macula Greek and Hebrew corpora,
            syntactic treebanks, semantic domain data, and lexicons. XQuery
            or XPath expressions are declared directly in pipeline YAML, and
            results flow into downstream LLM steps as structured context. This
            is the natural complement of BaseX's role in existing XML publishing
            pipelines, and the integration point at which Scripture Pipelines
            connects most directly to the XML database tradition that Balisage
            audiences will recognize.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>DuckDB tabular analytics</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-duckdb"/>: A
            <code>type: duckdb</code> step type allows pipelines to execute SQL
            queries against structured tabular data (CSV, TSV, Parquet, JSON).
            DuckDB is an in-process analytical database optimized for data science
            workflows — it runs without a server, loads data directly from files,
            and executes aggregations and joins at speed. This is the natural fit
            for statistical analysis: frequency distributions across a corpus,
            co-occurrence matrices for lexical studies, morphological feature
            counts, or passage-level metrics that require grouping and aggregation.
            The query results flow into downstream LLM steps as structured context,
            allowing the model to interpret patterns the SQL has surfaced.</para>
          </listitem>        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ds-registry">
        <title>Dataset Registry and Automatic Provisioning</title>
        <para>Scripture Pipelines maintains a dataset registry (<code>~/.sp/datasets/</code>)
          that catalogs available scholarly datasets with their identifiers, formats,
          licenses, and download locations. When a pipeline declares a data dependency,
          the engine checks the registry, downloads the dataset if needed, and caches
          it locally. This removes the manual step of "find the right data source,
          download it, and put it where the pipeline expects it." The registry currently
          catalogs 20+ datasets, including:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Macula Greek and Hebrew</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-macula-greek"/> <xref linkend="ref-macula-hebrew"/> — Full
            morphologically annotated corpora with syntactic dependency treebanks for
            both the Greek New Testament and Hebrew Bible (Clear-Bible, CC BY-SA 4.0).
            Includes lemma, gloss, morphology, and complete syntactic trees with head
            and dependent relationships.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>ACAI (Ancient Chains of Annotation Integration)</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-acai"/>
            — Biblical entity annotations covering people, places, flora, fauna,
            deities, groups, realia, and keyterms, anchored to Macula node IDs
            (Rick Brannan / Mission Mutual, CC BY-SA 4.0)</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Levinsohn discourse features</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-lgntdf"/> <xref linkend="ref-hotdf"/> — Word-level
            discourse grammar annotations for both the Greek New Testament (LGNTDF) and
            Hebrew Old Testament (HOTDF by Levinsohn &amp; Samuel), encoding cataphoric
            focus markers, point-of-departure shifts, boundary markers, and discourse
            feature elements</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>SDBH (Semantic Dictionary of Biblical Hebrew)</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-sdbh"/>
            — Lexical database for Hebrew terms with semantic domains and glosses</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>MorphHB</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-morphhb"/> — Morphological annotations
            for the Hebrew Bible with lemma and part-of-speech data</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Greek and Hebrew syntax trees</emphasis> — Additional
            treebank datasets for syntactic analysis (Clear-Bible Trees project)</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Alignment datasets</emphasis> — Word-level alignments
            between Hebrew/Greek and English translations</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Parser framework datasets</emphasis> — Training data
            and lexical resources for syntactic parsers</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis>Tyndale Bible Dictionary</emphasis> <xref linkend="ref-tyndale-dictionary"/> — Reference
            entries for people, places, and concepts</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The registry is extensible: new datasets can be added by any project,
          and the schema supports version constraints, alternative download mirrors,
          and format specifications that allow the engine to route data to the
          appropriate step type (BaseX for XML collections, DuckDB for tabular data,
          direct file access for JSON and TSV).</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="workflow-drivers">
    <title>Workflow Drivers and the Editorial Lifecycle</title>

    <section xml:id="iteration-axes">
      <title>What Drives the Pipeline</title>
      <para>Most Scripture Pipelines scholarly workflows are organized around one of three
        iteration axes, which determine what the <code>for-each</code> loop
        iterates over and what the pipeline considers one unit of work:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Text-driven:</emphasis> the passage or book is
          the primary unit. A pipeline runs per pericope, per chapter, or per
          book — as in Discourse Flow (iterating over Levinsohn-derived
          pericopes) or the Hebrew Phrasing pipeline (iterating over verse
          chunks). The text reference is the entry point; all other data serves
          the text.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Ontology-driven:</emphasis> a structured
          entity list is the primary unit. The ACAI entity database, for
          example, enumerates all people, places, flora, fauna, deities, groups,
          realia, and keyterms in the Bible. A storytelling dictionary pipeline
          iterates over ACAI entities — one pipeline run generates one article;
          the full dictionary emerges from running the pipeline over the complete
          entity list in citation-frequency order.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Lexeme-driven:</emphasis> a lemma from a
          lexicon or a frequency list is the primary unit. The SemLex Greek
          pipeline iterates over lemmas in a status spreadsheet, processing each
          one through gather-evidence, build-senses, and verify-citations passes.
          The relevant text passages are gathered as evidence for the lexeme, not
          the other way around.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>In practice these axes combine: a discourse analysis pipeline may
        be text-driven but pull entity data from ACAI and lexical data from
        a Greek lexicon as enrichment context for each pericope. The pipeline
        language imposes no constraint on which axis is primary; the structure
        of the <code>for-each</code> loop and the data sources loaded in
        function steps determine it.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="editorial-lifecycle">
      <title>Document Management at Generation Scale</title>
      <para>Scripture Pipelines changes the resource model for scholarly
        reference work. A project that once required a large team of
        specialists over many years can now be approached with a very small
        group: one person who knows how to design and maintain Scripture
        Pipelines projects; a handful of domain scholars who can evaluate
        output quality and catch errors that only subject-matter expertise
        can recognize; and focus groups of end users — translators, pastors,
        students — who can tell whether the output actually works for people
        who are not specialists. The pipeline handles the mechanical work of
        applying the full weight of the available datasets to every unit of
        analysis. The humans provide everything else: the vision of what the
        resource should be, the domain knowledge to know which datasets are
        relevant and trustworthy, the theological and linguistic expertise to
        catch what the model gets wrong, and the judgment to decide when output
        meets the bar for the communities it is meant to serve. The AI does not
        know that Levinsohn's discourse feature annotations exist, or that they
        are the right data source for pericope segmentation, until I made that
        architectural decision after studying that literature. The same
        is true in every case study in this paper: I brought the
        vision; the pipeline made it executable.</para>
      <para>This compressed resource model does not sacrifice thoroughness —
        it makes thoroughness possible in the first place. A lexicographer
        working alone cannot personally evaluate every papyrus citation for
        every lemma. A pipeline can gather and organize that evidence
        systematically; the scholar reviews the synthesis. The result is
        scholarly work grounded in a fuller evidence base than any individual
        could manually assemble.</para>
      <para>The compressed team creates its own management challenge:
        coordinating feedback from scholars and focus groups, tracking which
        generated outputs have been reviewed and revised, and ensuring that
        editorial changes are not silently overwritten by the next pipeline
        run. Traditional document management problems resurface with new
        urgency when pipelines can generate hundreds of structured artifacts
        in a single run. A lexicographer now faces an Obsidian vault
        containing entries for the 500 most frequent Greek lemmas — all
        generated overnight, all needing review, some excellent, some
        requiring significant revision, and some silently wrong in ways that
        only a domain expert can recognize. The generation speed creates a
        new bottleneck: not producing content, but tracking, auditing, and
        approving it.</para>
      <para>Scripture Pipelines' current approach uses filesystem directory structures as
        the primary management layer. Generated artifacts live in directories
        that can be imported directly into Obsidian, Notion, or Google Docs as
        note collections or document sets, leveraging those tools' existing
        features for linking, tagging, commenting, and status tracking. This
        keeps the editorial infrastructure in tools that domain experts already
        use, rather than requiring them to learn a specialized review
        interface.</para>
      <para>For Paratext-integrated workflows, USX 3.1 output from Scripture Pipelines pipelines
        can be loaded directly into Paratext projects, making the generated
        content a draft translation note or study aid that editors work with
        in the same environment as the translation itself. This is the natural
        end state for the Paratext USFM 3.1 / USX 3.1 integration described above: the
        pipeline reads from a Paratext project and, after editorial review,
        writes back to it.</para>
      <para>The central discipline that keeps this workable is clarity about
        the <emphasis>authoritative source</emphasis>. When a pipeline produces
        a lexicon entry or a pericope analysis and an editor revises it, that
        revised file is now the authoritative version. Re-running the pipeline
        would overwrite it. Scripture Pipelines handles this through two
        mechanisms.
        First, the <code>saveas</code> field writes to explicit, versioned
        paths — the history of every generated artifact is in
        <code>git log</code>. Second, the <code>sp init
        --update</code> flag regenerates only files that carry the
        <code>&lt;!-- Generated by sp init --&gt;</code> marker,
        leaving hand-edited files untouched. The same principle should be
        applied to pipeline outputs: files that have entered editorial review
        should be protected from regeneration, while files still in the
        generation phase can be freely overwritten.</para>
      <para>The practical workflow that emerges is a two-phase process.
        In the generation phase, I iterate on prompts,
        intermediate JSON, and output templates — using
        <code>--stop-after</code> and <code>--rewind-to</code> to refine
        individual steps — until the output quality consistently meets the
        bar for editorial review. Then the editorial phase begins: the
        generated batch moves to human reviewers, the directory becomes
        read-only to the pipeline, and editors work in Obsidian, Notion,
        or Paratext. The two phases should not overlap — and the versioned
        filesystem makes it straightforward to see when they do. Future
        tooling will make the boundary explicit with diff-based staleness
        detection: when a prompt changes after editors have touched its
        outputs, the system flags the affected files as requiring editorial
        re-review before the regeneration is accepted.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="case-studies">
    <title>Case Study: Ears to Hear</title>
    <para>Scripture Pipelines serves multiple communities: scholars producing
      lexicons, translation teams working with discourse analyses, beginning
      students learning biblical languages through structured annotations,
      and study groups working through Scripture together. The resources span
      a wide range — from highly technical (lexicographic sense distinctions,
      morphological analyses) to accessible (inductive Bible study questions,
      narrative summaries). But the ultimate purpose is not merely to produce
      resources. It is to make Scripture more accessible, more carefully
      understood, more deeply engaged — by scholars, yes, but also by readers
      in communities worldwide who bring no academic training yet read these
      texts with wisdom the academy often lacks. Every freely licensed lexicon,
      every grammatical analysis, every discourse structure ultimately exists
      to serve this end: getting people reading Scripture, noticing what is
      actually there, and carrying something from that encounter into their lives.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: Edit this list.</emphasis> Scripture Pipelines
      is currently being used for:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Semantic Lexicon of Biblical Greek (SemLex Greek)</emphasis>
        — A multi-pass pipeline producing lexicon entries grounded in the full
        Hellenistic corpus (NT, LXX, papyri, inscriptions), licensed CC BY-SA 4.0</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Hebrew Phrasing</emphasis> — Grammatical
        phrase analysis of the Hebrew Bible using Macula Hebrew morphological data</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Discourse Flow (Greek NT)</emphasis> —
        Book-level discourse analyses synthesizing Levinsohn features, Macula annotations,
        and narrative structure</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Hebrew Discourse Flow</emphasis> —
        Old Testament book-level discourse analysis pipeline</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Ears to Hear</emphasis> — Leader's
        guide generation for inductive Bible study, producing questions and
        narrative summaries from discourse analyses</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Internalization Questions</emphasis> —
        Scripture engagement questions designed to help readers internalize biblical content</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">SDBH Helpers</emphasis> — Support
        tools for the Semantic Dictionary of Biblical Hebrew</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Image Scene Descriptions</emphasis> —
        Generating textual descriptions of biblical scenes for visual aids</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Paratext Pipelines</emphasis> —
        Integration with Paratext Bible translation software workflows</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Macula LXX Greek</emphasis> —
        Processing and analysis of the Septuagint Greek text</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The following detailed case study focuses on Ears to Hear, which
      illustrates how Scripture Pipelines synthesizes scholarly datasets into
      resources for community Bible study — bridging the gap between technical
      scholarship and accessible study materials.</para>

    <section xml:id="ears-to-hear">
      <title>Ears to Hear: Leaders' Guide Generation from Structured Data Synthesis</title>
      <para>The Ears to Hear project illustrates the full range of what
        Scripture Pipelines makes possible: it synthesizes discourse analyses —
        hierarchical structures with manually annotated rhetorical features,
        the kind of technical apparatus scholars spend years learning to read —
        together with lexical data, morphological annotations, and entity
        information, then transforms that scholarly infrastructure into leaders'
        guides for everyday Bible study groups. The scholarly data is there, but
        it is deployed with care: in the right doses, at the right time, with
        deliberate pedagogy. A cultural note about honor and shame appears
        exactly when the group is ready to notice what it illuminates in the
        text, not as front-loaded encyclopedia entries. A lexical observation
        about what a Greek verb carries appears when the scene makes it matter,
        not as a grammar lecture. The pipeline serves the encounter; the
        scholarship serves the reader. The goal is not to produce scholars —
        though it creates scaffolding for those who want to climb toward deeper
        study — but to get people reading Scripture together: noticing what is
        actually in the text, asking questions that emerge from observation,
        and carrying something from the encounter that belongs to them.</para>
      <para>Ears to Hear operates as a consumer of the Scripture Pipelines engine
        from a separate repository (available at <link xlink:href="https://github.com/nida-institute/ears-to-hear"
        >https://github.com/nida-institute/ears-to-hear</link>).
        This case study focuses on how the project synthesizes multiple structured
        data sources — discourse analyses, lexical data, entity information,
        and linguistic annotations — into leaders' guides designed for oral
        study groups in diverse cultural contexts. It also examines the
        challenges of AI-assisted scholarship: how to keep LLM output grounded
        in source data, how to maintain reproducibility, and how to build
        shared understanding between human scholar and AI collaborator before
        the work actually produces trustworthy results.</para>

      <section xml:id="ears-book-summaries">
        <title>Book Summaries: Synthesizing Discourse Analysis and Structured Data</title>
        <para>Before generating passage-level leaders' guides, Ears to Hear
          first produces book-level context summaries. These summaries synthesize
          data from multiple sources:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Discourse-flow analyses</emphasis> —
            Hierarchical structures (divisions, pericopes, segments) with
            manually annotated features: topic, genre, participant tracking,
            rhetorical devices, and structural markers. For NT books, these
            come from the discourse-flow project (itself a Scripture Pipelines
            consumer); for OT books, from discourse-flow-hebrew.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">ACAI entity database</emphasis> —
            People, places, and things with descriptions, relationships, and
            verse-level occurrences.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Biblical lexicons</emphasis> —
            Word-sense data for Hebrew and Greek terms, including semantic
            notes, glosses, and usage patterns.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Source texts</emphasis> —
            WLC (Hebrew) for OT, SBLGNT (Greek) for NT, with morphological
            annotations.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>The pipeline (<code>build-book.yaml</code> and its dependencies)
          first loads discourse-flow JSON to extract scene boundaries, then
          iterates over each scene to produce verse-level enrichment (entities,
          lexical data, embodied and emotional analysis), scene-level synthesis
          (tension threads, character arcs, structural features), and finally
          book-level summary (narrative arc, tension threads consolidated across
          scenes, character arcs, structural pivots, and embodied context).</para>
        <para>The discourse-flow structure establishes the scene boundaries that
          Ears to Hear uses to build outlines. Each scene entry includes the
          canonical reference, discourse-annotated boundary markers (asyndeton,
          aspect shifts, participant changes), and structural metadata. The
          following excerpt shows two scenes from the Mark discourse-flow
          output:</para>
        <figure xml:id="fig-discourse-flow-structure">
          <title>Discourse Flow scene structure for Mark (from scene-overlay.json)</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[{
  "book": "Mark",
  "book_code": "MRK",
  "scene_count": 26,
  "scenes": [
    {
      "scene_id": "MRK-001",
      "sequence": 1,
      "canonical_reference": "Mark 1:1-13",
      "opening_verse": "1:1",
      "closing_verse": "1:13",
      "e2h_title": "Wilderness Voices Announce the Stronger One",
      "section_title": "The Prologue: The Way Prepared",
      "scene_type": "narrative",
      "primary_participants": ["John the Baptist", "Jesus", "the crowds"],
      "physical_setting": "The Jordan River and the Judean wilderness...",
      "heart_state_shift": "Jesus moves from hidden private identity to
        publicly revealed and commissioned Son.",
      "is_subdivision": false,
      "parent_section_ref": null,
      "boundary_confidence": "high",
      "boundary_rationale": "Major discourse-flow boundary: asyndeton at
        1:1 opens book; clear thematic/aspectual shift at 1:14."
    },
    {
      "scene_id": "MRK-002",
      "sequence": 2,
      "canonical_reference": "Mark 1:14-20",
      "opening_verse": "1:14",
      "closing_verse": "1:20",
      "e2h_title": "Jesus Calls Fishermen to Follow Him",
      "section_title": "Jesus' Inaugural Preaching and the Call of the
        First Disciples",
      "scene_type": "narrative",
      "primary_participants": ["Jesus", "Simon", "Andrew", "James", "John"],
      "physical_setting": "The shores of the Sea of Galilee, where
        fishermen are casting and mending their nets.",
      "heart_state_shift": "Simon, Andrew, James, and John transition from
        fishermen to followers of Jesus...",
      "is_subdivision": false,
      "parent_section_ref": null,
      "boundary_confidence": "high",
      "boundary_rationale": "Opening: New subject ('ὁ Ἰησοῦς'),
        over-encoding, and aspect shift (aorist to present) at 1:14;
        Highlighter ('ὅτι') and Focus+ ('πεπλήρωται ὁ καιρὸς') at 1:15
        mark a new proclamation. Closing: Asyndeton and new subject at 1:20."
    }
  ]
}]]></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <para>The <code>boundary_rationale</code> fields cite specific Levinsohn
          discourse features (asyndeton, aspect shifts, participant over-encoding,
          Highlighter and Focus+ markers) that justify the segmentation. These
          discourse-linguistic judgments, made upstream in the Discourse Flow
          pipeline, prevent the LLM from imposing arbitrary chapter divisions.
          The Ears to Hear pipeline receives these boundaries as input and builds
          its study materials respecting the discourse structure of the text.</para>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Discourse Terminology and Hierarchical
          Mapping.</emphasis> Discourse analysts use a technical vocabulary to
          describe textual structure. A <emphasis>discourse unit</emphasis> is any
          coherent span of text with internal unity and clear boundaries — ranging
          from a single clause to an entire book. A <emphasis>pericope</emphasis>
          (from Greek <emphasis role="ital">περικοπή</emphasis>, "section cut
          around") is a self-contained narrative episode or teaching unit,
          typically spanning several verses to a chapter. A <emphasis>segment</emphasis>
          is a smaller unit within a pericope, often corresponding to a scene
          change, participant shift, or thematic development within the larger
          episode. In Levinsohn's framework, these boundaries are identified
          through grammatical and discourse markers: asyndeton (absence of
          connectives), aspect shifts (change from perfective to imperfective),
          participant over-encoding (re-introducing a known participant with full
          description), and explicit boundary particles.</para>
        <para>The Ears to Hear project maps this discourse structure into a
          three-level hierarchy: <emphasis>divisions</emphasis> (major sections of
          a book, corresponding to large discourse units), <emphasis>sections</emphasis>
          (individual pericopes, what the Discourse Flow pipeline calls "scenes"),
          and <emphasis>passages</emphasis> (the verse ranges within a scene for
          which leaders' guide questions are generated). The <code>scene_id</code>
          field in scene-overlay.json serves as the stable identifier linking
          discourse analysis to downstream enrichment and question generation.
          The <code>is_subdivision</code> and <code>parent_section_ref</code>
          fields encode hierarchical nesting when a pericope contains significant
          internal segments that warrant separate treatment. This mapping preserves
          the scholarly rigor of discourse-linguistic segmentation while presenting
          the structure in terms accessible to Bible study leaders who may be
          unfamiliar with technical discourse terminology.</para>
        <para>The book summary prompt (<code>bookish-book-summary.gpt</code>)
          requires the LLM to account for its sources. For the
          <code>social_dynamics</code> field, every claimed pattern must cite
          at least two verse references. For <code>character_arcs</code>, the
          LLM must describe observable actions (what characters do and say),
          not psychological states, and cite specific verses. For
          <code>structural_pivots</code>, it must describe what changes before
          and after the pivot, not merely assert significance. The prompt
          explicitly forbids inventing material not visible in the input
          scene-synthesis data.</para>
        <para>The following excerpt shows the <code>narrative_arc</code> and
          one <code>tension_thread</code> from the Mark book summary, produced
          by synthesizing scene-level data across all 26 scenes in the Gospel:</para>
        <figure xml:id="fig-ears-book-summary">
          <title>Book summary excerpt for Mark (from book-hierarchy.json)</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[{
  "book": "Mark",
  "narrative_arc": "Mark opens with Jesus's public emergence in Galilee,
    marked by prophetic fulfillment, baptism, and early demonstrations of
    unique authority. The narrative unfolds through a rapid succession of
    exorcisms, healings, and confrontations between Jesus, religious
    authorities, insiders, and outsiders, primarily in Galilee (Mark 1-8).
    A pivotal shift occurs at Caesarea Philippi, when Peter confesses Jesus
    as Messiah, and the story turns southward toward Jerusalem. From this
    point, Jesus repeatedly predicts his suffering, engages in escalating
    conflict with authorities, and instructs the disciples on the cost of
    following him. The final third centers on Jerusalem: public acclaim at
    Jesus's entry, mounting opposition, betrayal, crucifixion, and—abruptly—
    an empty tomb and the commissioning of flawed followers. The book's
    geography traces a clear arc: Galilee → journey south → Jerusalem and
    the Temple → the cross and the empty tomb.",
  "tension_threads": [
    {
      "id": "mrk-authority-contest",
      "label": "Contested Authority: Who can include, restore, or judge?",
      "description": "From Galilee to Jerusalem, Jesus's authority is
        repeatedly challenged by religious leaders, family, and even his own
        disciples. This thread emerges in early exorcisms and healings
        (MRK-003), intensifies in Sabbath controversies and public debates
        (MRK-007, MRK-021, MRK-022), and culminates in the passion narrative
        where both his authority and identity are on trial. The thread is
        dramatically transformed at the cross, as an outsider recognizes
        Jesus as God's Son.",
      "scene_ids": ["MRK-003", "MRK-005", "MRK-006", "MRK-007", "MRK-008",
                    "MRK-014", "MRK-021", "MRK-022", "MRK-025"],
      "resolution": "transformed"
    }
  ]
}]]></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <para>This book-level data then flows into passage-level pipelines,
          providing leaders with narrative and thematic context before the
          first session begins.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ears-question-generation">
        <title>Sample Question Output: Scene-Based Inductive Questions</title>
        <para>The passage-level pipeline produces leaders' guides organized
          by scene and interpretive lens. Each scene receives questions under
          four lenses: <emphasis>Bodies</emphasis> (the physical, observable
          world), <emphasis>Hearts</emphasis> (inner life revealed through
          observable actions), <emphasis>Connecting</emphasis> (questions
          that draw observed textual tension into participants' lived
          experience), and <emphasis>Naming</emphasis> (a short scene title
          participants choose to carry the story). Questions are first
          generated as abstract syntax trees (ASTs) in JSON intermediate
          files, then rendered to Markdown and USX 3.1.</para>
        <para>The following excerpt shows the Bodies and Hearts questions for
          one scene from Mark 12:18–27, generated April 1, 2026, showing the current
          quality of pipeline output:</para>
        <figure xml:id="fig-ears-mark12">
          <title>Leaders' guide excerpt for Mark 12:18–27 (from April 1, 2026 pipeline run)</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[## Scene 1: Seven Brothers, One Wife

*Citation: Mark 12:18-27*

---

### 👣 Enter the Scene with Your Body (Mark 12:18-27)

Let's hear this part of the story again and pay attention to what it would
be like to be in this scene. What you would you see, hear, smell, taste, or
physically feel? How are people sitting or standing? What do they touch?
How close are they? How are they moving?

#### 👀 Notice

Let's start with what the scene shows us about bodies, senses, space,
and movement.

_Perspective: the Sadducees_

* What do the Sadducees do at the beginning of this scene?

* What do the Sadducees say to Jesus about Moses and marriage?

* What scenario do the Sadducees describe involving seven brothers and a woman?

* What final question do the Sadducees ask Jesus about the resurrection?

_Perspective: Jesus_

* What does Jesus do in response to the Sadducees' question?

* What does Jesus say about marriage after the resurrection?

    * What passage from Moses does Jesus mention in his answer?

    * What final statement does Jesus make about God and the living?

#### 💭 Imagine

Now let's imagine this moment from each perspective, still using the
same body questions.

_Background:_
The Sadducees were a wealthy, priestly group in Jerusalem, influential in
the Temple and known for denying the resurrection. They often debated
doctrinal matters with Jesus, seeking to defend their status and beliefs
before the people. Moses, as the lawgiver, is invoked as the authority for
the practice of levirate marriage: if a man dies without children, his
brother is to marry the widow to produce offspring for the deceased. This
legal tradition grounds the Sadducees' question.

_Perspective: the Sadducees_

* You are one of the Sadducees standing before Jesus in the Temple. What
  do you do as you present your question?

    * You are one of the Sadducees. What story do you tell Jesus and those
      listening?

_Perspective: Jesus_

* You are Jesus, surrounded by the crowd and religious leaders. What do
  you say in response to the Sadducees' question?

### 🫀 Enter the Scene with Your Whole Heart (Mark 12:18-27)

Staying inside this scene, let's ask about people's hearts—where they set
their hearts, what is at stake, what they fear, and what they hope for.

#### 👀 Notice

Let's focus on what the text actually tells us about where people are
setting their hearts and what is at stake for them.

_Perspective: the Sadducees_

* Why do the Sadducees bring this question to Jesus?

_Perspective: Jesus_

* Why does Jesus respond so sharply to their question?

    * What is Jesus insisting on when he says God is 'of the living'?

### 👂 Let the Scene Speak to Us (Mark 12:18-27)

Let's notice where the same kinds of pressures, questions, and hopes from
this scene show up in our world today.

1. Have you or someone you know ever found yourself in a conversation where
   it felt like people were more interested in protecting their reputation
   or proving a point than actually seeking understanding?

2. Have you or someone you know ever witnessed someone unexpectedly shift a
   heated debate or tense conversation toward what actually matters most,
   even when everyone else is caught up in details or appearances?

### 🏷️ Step 4: Name the Scene

Let's choose a short name that captures what stood out to us so we can
carry this part of the story with us.
- Seven Brothers, One Wife
- God of the Living
- A Question in the Temple
- You Are Greatly Mistaken]]></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <para>Observe: Bodies questions begin with physical observation (Notice)
          before moving to embodied imagination; Hearts questions surface
          inner-life stakes grounded in observable actions; Connecting questions
          tie observed textual tension to lived experience without moralizing;
          Naming invites participants to choose their own title. Multiple
          perspectives are maintained consistently across sections. Source-language
          text appears alongside English translation, both fetched via MCP.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ears-leader-intro">
        <title>Leader's Introduction: Preparing the Way</title>
        <para>Before the questions begin, each leader's guide includes an
          introduction designed to help the facilitator prepare. This is not
          scholarly apparatus or exegetical commentary—it is practical
          orientation written for someone who needs to understand what the
          session will feel like and what challenges or insights might emerge.
          The following excerpt from the Mark 12:18–27 guide (generated April 1,
          2026) shows the introduction structure:</para>
        <figure xml:id="fig-ears-intro">
          <title>Leader's introduction excerpt for Mark 12:18–27</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[### 2. What This Passage Does

This passage draws the conflict between Jesus and the Jerusalem authorities
into sharper focus. The Sadducees' question is meant to trap Jesus, but he
turns it into a moment of revelation—correcting their misunderstanding and
declaring the hope of resurrection in front of all. Jesus' answer doesn't
just silence the Sadducees; it reframes what is truly at stake: not just
technical arguments about the law, but trust in God's ongoing, life-giving
presence.

Within Mark's story, this is part of a series of public tests where Jesus
is challenged again and again, each time revealing something deeper about
who he is and what God is like. Here, Jesus claims the authority to interpret
Scripture and to reveal God's heart. He sets the stage for the next question—
about the greatest commandment—and moves the narrative closer to the final
showdowns that will lead to his arrest.

---

### 3. Expect Your Group to Connect With

- **Feeling the pressure to defend your reputation or beliefs when
  challenged in public**—like the Sadducees, who ask their question not out
  of curiosity, but to protect their standing.
- **Experiencing conversations where people care more about proving a point
  than truly listening or seeking understanding.**
- **Witnessing someone cut through a heated debate to name what really
  matters, shifting the focus from technicalities to deeper truths.**
- **Wondering what is at stake when we talk about hope, life, and what God
  is really like—especially when others are skeptical or dismissive.**

---

### 4. As You Prepare

Read this passage through a few times, slowly, and look at each section
alongside its questions. Notice how the questions are structured: some are
Open—like "What do the Sadducees do at the beginning of this scene?"—
inviting your group to explore what the text shows; others are Guiding—
such as "What passage from Moses does Jesus mention in his answer?"—
helping your group focus on key details or turning points. The "Imagine"
prompts invite participants to step into the shoes of both the Sadducees
and Jesus, to feel the tension and the weight of public challenge.

You'll notice that cultural background appears where it's needed: brief
notes about who the Sadducees are, why Moses' law matters, and what the
burning bush means. You don't need to front-load these details—trust that
your group can pick them up as they go, and that the questions themselves
will spark curiosity and insight. Let the conversation breathe. If a question
doesn't fit your group, feel free to skip it or rephrase it. Your role is
to create space for discovery and honest engagement; you don't need to have
all the answers. Trust the process, and trust your group—they may notice
details or connections you haven't seen. Be present, and let the story do
its work.]]></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <para>The introduction serves multiple purposes: <emphasis>What This
          Passage Does</emphasis> orients the leader to the passage's role in
          the larger narrative arc; <emphasis>Expect Your Group to Connect
          With</emphasis> anticipates resonances between the biblical scene
          and participants' lived experience; <emphasis>As You Prepare</emphasis>
          coaches the facilitator on how to use the questions, where cultural
          background appears, and how to hold space for discovery. The overall
          purpose is to help the leader prepare to lead a group session—to
          become familiar with the material before the discussion begins,
          anticipate what the conversation might involve, and gain confidence
          in facilitating without needing to be a biblical scholar. Observe that
          this is not traditional study-Bible commentary—it addresses the leader
          directly, assumes they are not experts, and focuses on group
          dynamics rather than technical exegesis. The tone is conversational,
          practical, and encouraging. This material is generated by the
          <code>leadersguide-intro-ast.gpt</code> prompt, which receives the
          exegetical analysis and scene structures as input and produces
          orientation prose designed for facilitators who may have little formal
          training. Architecturally, the introduction is generated <emphasis>after</emphasis>
          all the Bodies, Hearts, and Connecting questions have been finalized—it
          is one of the last pipeline stages—even though it appears first in
          the final guide. This separation of generation order from presentation
          order allows the introduction prompt to reference the actual questions
          that were generated, describing their structure and coaching the leader
          on how to use them.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ears-prompt-structure">
        <title>Prompt Structure: Input, Output, Rules</title>
        <para>Ears to Hear prompts are declarative contracts specifying input
          data, output format, and generation rules. Each <code>.gpt</code>
          file has a YAML frontmatter declaring required inputs, output format,
          and a description; the prompt body then specifies task, input schema,
          output schema, and guardrails. The following excerpts from
          <code>leadersguide-bodies-ast.gpt</code> show the contract structure:</para>
        <figure xml:id="fig-ears-prompt-contract">
          <title>Prompt contract (YAML frontmatter and input specification)</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[---
prompt:
  requires:
    - passage
    - leadersguide_snippets
  format: json
  description: >-
    Rewrite Bodies snippet skeletons into globally accessible oral questions.
---

# Task
You receive `leadersguide_snippets.skeletons`, a precomputed array of
question skeletons built entirely from exegetical analysis. Your job
is NOT to generate new ideas. Simply rewrite each Bodies skeleton into
an inductive oral question while keeping every other field unchanged.

## Data You Receive
Each skeleton object includes:
- `id`, `section`, `list`, `scene_index`, `scene_title`, `citation`
- `perspective`, `question_role`, `anchor`, `anchor_type`, `source_excerpt`
- `source_paths`, `assumptions`, `background`, `background_sources`

Only process entries whose `section == "bodies"`. Preserve the original
ordering so Notice/Imagine pairings remain aligned.]]></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <para>The prompt contract makes explicit: (1) what input variables
          the LLM will receive (<code>passage</code>, <code>leadersguide_snippets</code>);
          (2) what output format is required (JSON); (3) the task is rewrite-only,
          not generate-new-content. Every field in the skeleton object is listed,
          so the LLM knows what data it has access to.</para>
        <para>The rules section of the prompt specifies output constraints:</para>
        <figure xml:id="fig-ears-prompt-rules">
          <title>Prompt rules excerpt (guardrails and field-specific constraints)</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[## Rewrite Rules
1. **Rewrite-only.** Turn the `anchor` text into a ≤15-word oral question.
   Stay in the third person, keep vocabulary globally accessible, and never
   add information that is not already present in either the `anchor` or
   the supplied `background` text.
2. **Notice vs. Imagine.**
   - `list == "Notice"`: No modal verbs (`might`, `would`, `could`). Ask
     for the concrete action, posture, or sensory fact already stated.
   - `list == "Imagine"`: You may use one modal verb to explore sensory
     implications, but you still may not introduce new facts.
3. **Question role.** Match the tone to `question_role`.
   - `open`: broad inductive invitation ("Tell me...", "What does...").
   - `guiding`: focused wh-question on a single observable detail.
4. **Active participants only.** Only generate a perspective block
   (Notice or Imagine) for a perspective whose character is *active*
   in the citation range — taking an action, speaking, or making a
   visible choice. A character who only *receives* action without
   speaking or responding does not warrant a perspective block.
5. **Perpetrator suppression (Imagine).** If a perspective's
   `source_excerpt` or `assumptions` show that this character beats,
   kills, throws, or physically assaults another character in this scene,
   do NOT output any `list == "Imagine"` skeletons for that perspective.
   Immersive "You are X, what is it like to..." questions must not be
   generated for perpetrators of violence.]]></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <para>These rules encode interpretive commitments (no new facts,
          globally accessible vocabulary, no immersive questions for perpetrators
          of violence) as testable constraints on LLM output. The prompt
          contract makes implicit editorial standards explicit and auditable.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ears-language-mediation">
        <title>Language Mediation: From Model to Embodied Context</title>
        <para>One of the intermediate steps in the Ears to Hear pipeline is
          the <emphasis>language</emphasis> analysis, which mediates between
          lexical data and embodied, scene-aware context. The pipeline loads
          enriched word-sense data for every lemma in a passage, then asks
          the LLM to synthesize this into scene-specific embodied and
          emotional notes. The output is a JSON file (<code>*_language.json</code>)
          that describes, for each key term, what a participant in that scene
          would physically experience or feel.</para>
        <para>The following excerpt from the language analysis for Mark 10:46
          shows how the pipeline converts lexical and morphological data into
          embodied context for the term <emphasis>τυφλός</emphasis> (blind):</para>
        <figure xml:id="fig-ears-language">
          <title>Language mediation excerpt for Mark 10:46 (from 41010046-41010052_language.json)</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[{
  "lemma": "τυφλός",
  "gloss": "blind",
  "source": "enriched",
  "semantic_notes": "Core: unable to see (MAT 11:5). In narratives,
    marks physical limitation and social vulnerability.",
  "embodied_notes": "No visual input; orientation by sound and touch.
    Head tilts toward voices; hands trace ground or cloak edge to
    locate objects. Eyes may be dry/irritated from dust; habitual
    squinting without visual focus.",
  "emotional_relational_notes": "Dependence on passersby for guidance
    and charity; others decide when to help or ignore. Limited mobility
    increases exposure to crowd mood and control."
}]]></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <para>This intermediate representation then flows into the
          <code>analyze_bodies</code> and <code>analyze_hearts</code> steps,
          grounding the exegetical analysis in the physical and emotional
          register of the text. The language mediation layer is where abstract
          lexical data becomes scene-specific embodied context — translating
          the model's semantic knowledge into the sensory and relational world
          of the passage.</para>
        <para>This layer is necessary because lexicons typically describe
          what a word <emphasis>means</emphasis>, not what someone experiences
          when the word names their condition or action. The language mediation
          step fills that gap, preparing context for downstream question
          generation that is meant to help participants enter the scene with
          their own bodies and hearts.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="ears-skills-collaboration">
        <title>Skills Files and Human-AI Collaboration Challenges</title>
        <para>Ears to Hear encodes its interpretive framework and workflow
          standards in a <code>.github/copilot-instructions.md</code> file
          at the repository root, and in domain-specific <code>SKILL.md</code>
          files in the <code>docs/skills/</code> directory. These files are
          not documentation for humans — they are persistent instructions for
          the AI collaborator, encoding domain knowledge, coding patterns,
          and workflow guardrails that the AI must follow.</para>
        <para>The <code>audit-prompts/SKILL.md</code> file is a case in point.
          It defines a read-only workflow for auditing <code>.gpt</code> prompt
          files for sprawl, convention compliance, and — most critically —
          for detecting when LLM output has been used as training data (examples)
          in prompts. The skill's preamble states the core principle:</para>
        <figure xml:id="fig-ears-skill-principle">
          <title>Core principle from audit-prompts/SKILL.md</title>
          <programlisting><![CDATA[## Core Principle: No LLM-Generated Training Data

**ABSOLUTE RULE:** Nothing produced by an LLM can ever be used as
training data (examples) in prompts. Period.

**Why this matters:**
- LLM output doesn't match user intent with sufficient precision
- AI-generated examples encode subtle patterns the AI already knows,
  not what you're trying to teach
- Examples must demonstrate the exact pattern you want, which requires
  human judgment
- Using LLM output as training creates circular reasoning and drift
  from intent

**What this means for audits:**
- Any new examples since last commit are SUSPECT until proven
  human-written
- At best, AI can propose examples for user approval (never auto-merged)
- Often, user must write examples themselves to ensure quality
- TODOs that get replaced with examples warrant extra scrutiny]]></programlisting>
        </figure>
        <para>This principle emerged from repeated failure modes in human-AI
          collaboration on prompt engineering:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">AI treating LLM output as
            training data.</emphasis> The AI would generate sample output,
            then propose adding that output as an example in the prompt —
            treating its own generation as ground truth. This creates circular
            reasoning: the AI learns from examples it generated, not from
            examples that demonstrate the user's intent.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Conflating training data with
            test cases.</emphasis> Test cases verify that a prompt produces
            correct output; training examples teach the LLM what correct output
            looks like. The AI repeatedly confused these, proposing to add
            test output as examples, which defeats the purpose of testing.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Solving the wrong problem.</emphasis>
            The AI would assume it understood the user's problem from a brief
            description, then implement a solution before confirming alignment.
            Often the AI's inferred problem was not the user's actual problem,
            resulting in wasted work and misalignment.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">The audit-prompt skill as a
            solution.</emphasis> The skill encodes a read-only audit workflow
            that forces the AI to report what it finds without making changes.
            This prevents premature implementation and gives the user visibility
            before committing to a direction. The skill explicitly forbids
            <code>replace_string_in_file</code> and <code>create_file</code>
            tools, ensuring the AI cannot act on its inferences without user
            approval.</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>But even with skills files, the fundamental constraint remains:
          <emphasis>the AI and the human must build a shared understanding
          before the work produces trustworthy results.</emphasis> The user
          still has to read the prompts in detail, read the data, and verify
          that the AI's understanding matches intent. Skills files reduce
          friction and encode common patterns, but they do not replace the
          need for the human scholar to remain the final arbiter of whether
          the output is correct. This is not a limitation of the current
          generation of AI — it is a structural feature of using AI for
          scholarly work: the AI does not have access to the user's intent
          except through the instructions and data it is given, and those
          instructions must be precise enough to constrain the AI's vast
          pattern-matching capacity to the narrow problem the user actually
          wants solved.</para>
        <para>Scripture Pipelines does not solve this problem. It makes it
          manageable. By externalizing prompts, requiring explicit input/output
          contracts, and persisting all intermediate results, it provides the
          visibility and auditability needed to catch misalignment before it
          propagates. But the human scholar must still do the reading, the
          checking, and the final judgment. The pipeline serves scholarship;
          it does not replace it.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="related-work">
    <title>Related Work</title>

    <section xml:id="rw-xproc">
      <title>XProc</title>
      <para>XProc is the closest structural parallel to Scripture Pipelines: both are
        declarative pipeline languages that define a graph of steps with named
        ports, typed inputs and outputs, and compound step composition. XProc
        3.0's extension to non-XML document types, its <code>p:for-each</code>
        step over sequences, and its atomic/compound step model are all
        recognizable cousins of Scripture Pipelines constructs.</para>
      <para>The fundamental difference is the document model. XProc pipelines
        process documents flowing through ports; the unit of computation is
        a document transformation. Scripture Pipelines pipelines generate knowledge by
        passing structured context to language models; the unit of computation
        is a prompt with a contract and a JSON response. XProc has no concept
        of a prompt, a token budget, a model temperature, or a retry condition
        on model output quality. Scripture Pipelines has no concept of a serialization
        pipeline or namespace-aware document trees.</para>
      <para>In practice the two are complementary. Scripture Pipelines handles the
        LLM-generation phase; XProc handles downstream document transformation.
        The Discourse Flow pipeline, for example, produces USX as one of its
        output formats — that USX is a natural input to an XProc pipeline for
        subsequent publishing transforms. Similarly, TEI documents produced by
        scholarly editors are natural inputs to Scripture Pipelines function steps that
        prepare context for LLM analysis. TEI's milestone elements, standoff
        annotations, and <code>&lt;interp&gt;</code> infrastructure already
        provide the kind of structured scholarly overlay that Scripture Pipelines pipelines
        can read, generate, and augment.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="rw-langchain">
      <title>LangChain, LlamaIndex, and Haystack</title>
      <para>LangChain and LlamaIndex are the dominant Python frameworks for LLM
        application development. Both are imperative: pipelines are Python code
        that chains objects together. This gives maximum flexibility but removes
        the properties that matter most for scholarly workflows — readability by
        non-programmers, declarative auditability, and separation of pipeline
        logic from prompt content. A LangChain chain is not something a
        lexicographer can read and modify. A Scripture Pipelines pipeline is.</para>
      <para>Neither framework treats intermediate outputs as first-class
        persistent artifacts. LangChain's memory and caching mechanisms are
        designed for chat history, not for the multi-day, multi-pass generation
        workflows of lexicography or discourse analysis where being able to rerun
        from step three without repeating steps one and two is essential
        economics, not a convenience. Neither framework has a concept analogous
        to prompt contracts: there is no mechanism that prevents a prompt from
        being called with missing inputs, and no validation before a run begins
        that the data flow is coherent.</para>
      <para>Haystack is closer in spirit — it supports YAML pipeline
        declarations and has a stronger emphasis on structured pipelines — but
        its design center is retrieval-augmented generation and document QA,
        not the mixed deterministic-plus-generative scholarly workflows that
        Scripture Pipelines targets.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="rw-dspy">
      <title>DSPy</title>
      <para>DSPy takes a fundamentally different approach: rather than having
        authors write prompts, it compiles prompt programs from signatures and
        optimizes them automatically against a metric. This is powerful for
        tasks with well-defined correctness criteria, but it is antithetical to
        the requirements of scholarly pipeline work. A lexicographer needs to
        read, understand, and argue about every instruction given to the model.
        An automatically compiled prompt is a black box. The Abbott-Smith audit
        pattern described in the SemLex section — where the prompt explicitly
        instructs the model to enumerate its sources and record its reasoning —
        is not expressible in a compiled prompt framework. The audit trail
        requires human authorship of the prompt.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="rw-gate-uima">
      <title>GATE and UIMA</title>
      <para>GATE (General Architecture for Text Engineering) and UIMA (Unstructured
        Information Management Architecture) are annotation pipeline frameworks
        with long histories in computational linguistics and NLP. Both support
        TEI-aware processing configurations and provide rich annotation schemas
        over document structure. Both treat the pipeline as a graph of processing
        resources that annotate a document in sequence — a model structurally
        similar to Scripture Pipelines' step sequence.</para>
      <para>The divergence is again in the generation model. GATE and UIMA
        pipelines analyze and annotate existing text; they do not generate new
        text or make calls to probabilistic language models as first-class
        operations. Incorporating an LLM into a GATE pipeline is possible but
        requires custom Java components and treats the LLM as an external
        service rather than a native pipeline citizen. Scripture Pipelines inverts this:
        the LLM call is the primary step type, and deterministic processing
        is the extension point.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="rw-prefect-airflow">
      <title>Workflow Orchestration Frameworks</title>
      <para>General-purpose workflow orchestration tools — Prefect, Airflow,
        Luigi — address the scheduling, dependency tracking, and failure recovery
        of data pipelines at scale. Their DAG model and task dependency
        declarations are structurally related to Scripture Pipelines' step sequence.
        However, these frameworks target data engineering workflows executed by
        developers; they have no concept of a prompt contract, no support for
        LLM-specific concerns (model selection, token budgets, output type
        parsing), and no provision for the scholar-facing readability and
        human editorial loop that Scripture Pipelines is designed around. They are also
        substantially more complex to install and operate than a single
        self-contained binary.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================================ -->
  <section xml:id="conclusion">
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    <para>The world of biblical and linguistic scholarship has accumulated
      extraordinary open datasets — morphological treebanks, discourse
      annotations, documentary papyri, lexicographic databases, ontologies,
      semantic domains — that
      represent decades of scholarly labor and are largely inaccessible to
      practitioners who need them most. The barrier is not availability;
      most of it is freely licensed. The barrier is the human capacity to
      synthesize it at scale and turn it into materials that translators,
      pastors, and students can actually use.</para>
    <para>Scripture Pipelines addresses this gap by making AI work like a
      careful research assistant rather than an unchecked generator. A lean
      team — a pipeline designer, a handful of scholars, and focus groups
      of real users — can now produce freely licensed reference materials
      grounded in the full breadth of available scholarly data: lexicons
      that account for every papyrus citation, discourse analyses that apply
      the complete Levinsohn dataset to every pericope, study guides derived
      from rigorous grammatical analysis rather than paraphrase. None of
      these were feasible for an underresourced project before.</para>
    <para>The infrastructure that makes this possible — declarative YAML
      pipelines, structured JSON intermediates with embedded accountability
      fields, persisted outputs at every step, prompt contracts, and
      rewind/stop-after debugging — is not primarily a technical achievement.
      It is a discipline: a set of working practices that keep the human
      scholar in the loop, make the provenance of every generated artifact
      traceable, and ensure that AI synthesis is grounded in the structured
      scholarly data it was given rather than in whatever a language model
      would produce without constraints. The format choices — YAML, JSON,
      Markdown, XML, each for its own purpose — reflect the same pragmatism:
      what works best here, not what wins the syntax debate.</para>
    <para>None of this diminishes the role of human expertise — it
      transforms how that expertise is applied. A scholar who knows that
      the Louw-Nida / SemDom question chain can navigate 1,792 semantic
      domains to a single word's classification in approximately four
      questions does not need less expertise to work with Scripture Pipelines
      than without it; they need more. The pipeline amplifies the reach of
      that insight across an entire corpus. A discourse analyst who
      recognizes the significance of Levinsohn's word-level annotations
      for pericope segmentation unlocks a dataset of 806 structural signals
      in 1 John alone that would otherwise remain invisible to any pipeline
      that didn't know to look. The dreaming, the problem framing, the
      choice of which scholarly tradition to ground a pipeline in, the
      judgment to know when the model's output is wrong, the taste to know
      what good enough means for a translator in the field — none of that
      is supplied by the tool. What changes is the leverage: a single
      scholar with deep domain knowledge and a well-designed pipeline can
      now produce work that would previously have required a large team
      and many years. Experience still counts. It just goes further.</para>
    <para>This is what The Kairos Project is for. When we say "a scholar with
      deep domain knowledge," we mean scholars worldwide — including those
      learning Greek and Hebrew outside traditional seminaries, multilingual
      learners who bring linguistic gifts that Western institutions have not
      recognized, translation teams who know their target audience in ways
      the academy never will. The goal is not to make Western scholars more
      productive; the goal is to democratize the tools so that scholarship
      can happen where it is needed, by people who have been told they are
      not qualified, producing resources together with the communities who
      will actually use them. Scripture Pipelines is infrastructure for that
      vision. It makes the open datasets — the treebanks, the lexicons, the
      discourse annotations — accessible to people who do not have a PhD
      from a Western university and do not need one to do rigorous work
      with the text. The Kairos Project exists to raise up scholars globally,
      not to preserve the Western academy's role as gatekeeper. The bidirectional
      flow between academy and church, between institution and field, is not
      a concession — it is the point.</para>
    <para>The projects reported here are early instances of a
      larger program. The dataset registry and system integrations provide
      the infrastructure for an expanding range of pipeline-producible scholarly
      materials. The goal is a world where the open data that scholars have
      painstakingly assembled becomes the shared foundation for work that
      communities worldwide do together — not resources provided for them,
      but scholarship they participate in creating.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ai-disclosure">
    <title>A Note on AI in the Writing of This Paper</title>
    <para>This paper was written with AI assistance, in a manner consistent
      with the principles it describes. The author used GitHub Copilot as a
      collaborator throughout: drafting passages, testing arguments, refining
      phrasing, and at several points returning to the saved chat histories
      from specific projects — the SemLex lexicon, the Hebrew Phrasing
      analysis, the Discourse Flow pipeline, Ears to Hear, and the
      Scripture Pipelines engine itself — the full record of prompts,
      responses, and revisions across each collaboration. The author shared
      those histories with the AI and reflected, project by project, on how
      the work had actually proceeded: what the human had directed, what
      the AI had contributed, where miscommunications had occurred and been
      corrected. Those reflection sessions became the primary source for the
      human-command section — the author described how the collaborations
      had gone, and the AI helped put those descriptions into prose that
      generalized across them.</para>
    <para>The James Kirk model applied. The author read everything, accepted
      or rejected or revised every sentence, and directed every significant
      turn in the argument. The AI did not decide what the paper should argue;
      it helped the author say what he had decided to argue. The paper's
      central claim — that human judgment, scholarly accountability, and
      community ownership are not transferable to a language model — was not
      undermined by the process of writing it this way. If anything, the
      process was an extended test of that claim, and the claim held.</para>
  </section>

  <bibliography>
    <title>References</title>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-abbott-smith">
      Abbott-Smith, G. <emphasis role="ital">A Manual Greek Lexicon of the New
      Testament</emphasis>. T&amp;T Clark, Edinburgh, 1937.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-louw-nida">
      Louw, J. P. and E. A. Nida. <emphasis role="ital">Greek-English Lexicon of the
      New Testament Based on Semantic Domains</emphasis>, 2 vols. United
      Bible Societies, New York, 1988.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-levinsohn-book">
      Levinsohn, S. H. <emphasis role="ital">Discourse Features of New Testament Greek:
      A Coursebook on the Information Structure of New Testament
      Greek</emphasis>, 2nd ed. SIL International, Dallas, 2000.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-lgntdf">
      Levinsohn, S. H. <emphasis role="ital">Levinsohn Greek New Testament Discourse
      Features (LGNTDF)</emphasis>. Data set. Biblical Humanities.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/biblicalhumanities/levinsohn"
        >https://github.com/biblicalhumanities/levinsohn</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-macula-greek">
      Clear Bible. <emphasis role="ital">Macula Greek Linguistic
      Datasets</emphasis>. Data set. CC BY 4.0.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/Clear-Bible/macula-greek"
        >https://github.com/Clear-Bible/macula-greek</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-macula-hebrew">
      Clear Bible. <emphasis role="ital">Macula Hebrew Linguistic
      Datasets</emphasis>. Data set. CC BY 4.0.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/Clear-Bible/macula-hebrew"
        >https://github.com/Clear-Bible/macula-hebrew</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-hotdf">
      Levinsohn, S. H. and D. Samuel. <emphasis role="ital">Hebrew Old Testament
      Discourse Features (HOTDF)</emphasis>. Data set. Nida Institute.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/nida-institute/levinsohn-samuel-hebrew"
        >https://github.com/nida-institute/levinsohn-samuel-hebrew</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-sdbh">
      United Bible Societies. <emphasis role="ital">Semantic Dictionary of Biblical
      Hebrew (SDBH)</emphasis>. Data set. Open license.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/ubsicap/ubs-open-license"
        >https://github.com/ubsicap/ubs-open-license</link>.
      <link xlink:href="https://semanticdictionary.org/"
        >https://semanticdictionary.org/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-morphhb">
      OpenScriptures. <emphasis role="ital">Hebrew Bible (morphhb): Parsed Hebrew
      Bible with Strong's numbers and morphology</emphasis>. Data set. MIT License.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/openscriptures/morphhb"
        >https://github.com/openscriptures/morphhb</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-tyndale-dictionary">
      Elwell, W. A. and P. W. Comfort (eds.). <emphasis role="ital">Tyndale Bible
      Dictionary</emphasis>. Tyndale House Publishers, Carol Stream, IL, 2001.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-duckdb">
      Raasveldt, M. and H. Mühleisen. <quote>DuckDB: an Embeddable Analytical
      Database.</quote> <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of the 2019 International
      Conference on Management of Data (SIGMOD)</emphasis>, pp. 1981–1984, 2019.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-sblgnt">
      Holmes, M. W. (ed.). <emphasis role="ital">The Greek New Testament: SBL
      Edition</emphasis>. Society of Biblical Literature and Logos Bible
      Software, Atlanta and Bellingham, 2010. Custom license.
      <link xlink:href="http://sblgnt.com/"
        >http://sblgnt.com/</link>.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/morphgnt/sblgnt"
        >https://github.com/morphgnt/sblgnt</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-bunning">
      Bunning, A. <emphasis role="ital">Center for New Testament Restoration:
      Transcriptions of Greek New Testament Manuscripts</emphasis>.
      <link xlink:href="https://greekcntr.org/"
        >https://greekcntr.org/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-acai">
      Brannan, R. <emphasis role="ital">ACAI</emphasis>. Mission Mutual, 2025.
      CC BY-SA 4.0. Dataset.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/BibleAquifer/ACAI"
        >https://github.com/BibleAquifer/ACAI</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-usfm">
      USFM/X Technical Committee. <emphasis role="ital">USFM/USX Technical
      Documentation</emphasis>.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/usfm-bible/tcdocs"
        >https://github.com/usfm-bible/tcdocs</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-scripture-burrito">
      Scripture Burrito Taskforce. <emphasis role="ital">Scripture Burrito: A
      Specification for Bible-Containing Containers</emphasis>.
      <link xlink:href="https://docs.burrito.bible/"
        >https://docs.burrito.bible/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-basex">
      Grün, C. et al. <emphasis role="ital">BaseX: The XML
      Database</emphasis>.
      <link xlink:href="https://basex.org/">https://basex.org/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-xproc3">
      Walsh, N. et al. <emphasis role="ital">XProc 3.0: An XML Pipeline
      Language</emphasis>. W3C Working Group Note, 2022.
      <link xlink:href="https://spec.xproc.org/3.0/xproc/"
        >https://spec.xproc.org/3.0/xproc/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-awesome-biblical-data">
      Nida Institute. <emphasis role="ital">Awesome Biblical Data: A Curated Catalog
      of Datasets and Tools for Biblical and Linguistic
      Scholarship</emphasis>. 2026–. CC BY-SA 4.0.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/nida-institute/awesome-biblical-data"
        >https://github.com/nida-institute/awesome-biblical-data</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-langchain">
      Chase, H. et al. <emphasis role="ital">LangChain</emphasis>. 2022–.
      <link xlink:href="https://www.langchain.com/"
        >https://www.langchain.com/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-llamaindex">
      Liu, J. et al. <emphasis role="ital">LlamaIndex</emphasis>. 2022–.
      <link xlink:href="https://www.llamaindex.ai/"
        >https://www.llamaindex.ai/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-haystack">
      deepset. <emphasis role="ital">Haystack: Open-Source LLM
      Framework</emphasis>. 2020–.
      <link xlink:href="https://haystack.deepset.ai/"
        >https://haystack.deepset.ai/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-dspy">
      Khattab, O. et al. <quote>DSPy: Compiling Declarative Language
      Model Calls into Self-Improving Pipelines.</quote>
      arXiv:2310.03714, 2023.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-gate">
      Cunningham, H. et al. <emphasis role="ital">Developing Language Processing
      Components with GATE (a User Guide)</emphasis>. University of
      Sheffield, 2011.
      <link xlink:href="https://gate.ac.uk/">https://gate.ac.uk/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-uima">
      Ferrucci, D. and A. Lally. <quote>UIMA: An Architectural Approach
      to Unstructured Information Processing in the Corporate Research
      Environment.</quote> <emphasis role="ital">Natural Language
      Engineering</emphasis> 10(3–4):327–348, 2004.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-papyri">
      <emphasis role="ital">papyri.info: Integrating Digital Papyrology</emphasis>.
      Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri and Heidelberger
      Gesamtverzeichnis der griechischen Papyrusurkunden Ägyptens.
      <link xlink:href="https://papyri.info/">https://papyri.info/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-perseus">
      Crane, G. (ed.). <emphasis role="ital">Perseus Digital Library</emphasis>.
      Tufts University.
      <link xlink:href="https://www.perseus.tufts.edu/"
        >https://www.perseus.tufts.edu/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-first1kgreek">
      Open Greek and Latin Project. <emphasis role="ital">First1KGreek: First
      Thousand Years of Greek</emphasis>.
      <link xlink:href="https://opengreekandlatin.github.io/First1KGreek/"
        >https://opengreekandlatin.github.io/First1KGreek/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-epidoc">
      EpiDoc Collaborative. <emphasis role="ital">EpiDoc: Epigraphic Documents in
      TEI XML</emphasis>.
      <link xlink:href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/"
        >https://epidoc.stoa.org/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-ears-to-hear">
      Robie, J. <emphasis role="ital">Ears to Hear</emphasis>. Nida Institute, 2025.
      <link xlink:href="https://github.com/nida-institute/ears-to-hear"
        >https://github.com/nida-institute/ears-to-hear</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-chafe-1994">
      Chafe, Wallace. <emphasis role="ital">Discourse, Consciousness, and Time: The Flow
      and Displacement of Conscious Experience in Speaking and Writing</emphasis>.
      University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 1994.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-robie-bar-2024">
      Robie, J. <quote>Artificial Intelligence and Bible Translation.</quote>
      <emphasis role="ital">Bible History Daily</emphasis>. Biblical Archaeology Society,
      January 3, 2024.
      <link xlink:href="https://www.biblicalarchaeology.org/daily/artificial-intelligence-and-bible-translation/"
        >https://www.biblicalarchaeology.org/daily/artificial-intelligence-and-bible-translation/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-vaswani-2017">
      Vaswani, A., Shazeer, N., Parmar, N., Uszkoreit, J., Jones, L.,
      Gomez, A. N., Kaiser, L., and Polosukhin, I. <quote>Attention is All
      You Need.</quote> <emphasis role="ital">Advances in Neural Information
      Processing Systems 30</emphasis> (NeurIPS 2017).
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-alammar-2018">
      Alammar, Jay. <quote>The Illustrated Transformer.</quote> 2018.
      <link xlink:href="https://jalammar.github.io/illustrated-transformer/"
        >https://jalammar.github.io/illustrated-transformer/</link>.
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-brown-2020">
      Brown, T. B., Mann, B., Ryder, N., Subbiah, M., Kaplan, J., Dhariwal, P.,
      Neelakantan, A., Shyam, P., Sastry, G., Askell, A., et al. <quote>Language
      Models are Few-Shot Learners.</quote> <emphasis role="ital">Advances in
      Neural Information Processing Systems 33</emphasis> (NeurIPS 2020).
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-wei-2022">
      Wei, J., Wang, X., Schuurmans, D., Bosma, M., Ichter, B., Xia, F., Chi, E.,
      Le, Q., and Zhou, D. <quote>Chain-of-Thought Prompting Elicits Reasoning
      in Large Language Models.</quote> <emphasis role="ital">Advances in
      Neural Information Processing Systems 35</emphasis> (NeurIPS 2022).
    </bibliomixed>

    <bibliomixed xml:id="ref-russell-2019">
      Russell, Stuart. <emphasis role="ital">Human Compatible: Artificial Intelligence
      and the Problem of Control</emphasis>. Viking, New York, 2019.
    </bibliomixed>

  </bibliography>

</article>
